<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The memoires of the Dutchess Mazarine out of French.</title>
            <title>Mémoires de Madame la duchesse Mazarin. English. 1676</title>
            <author>Mazarin, Hortense Mancini, duchesse de, 1646-1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60046</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S355</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28396</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10585855</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10585855</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45280</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60046)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45280)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1366:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The memoires of the Dutchess Mazarine out of French.</title>
                  <title>Mémoires de Madame la duchesse Mazarin. English. 1676</title>
                  <author>Mazarin, Hortense Mancini, duchesse de, 1646-1699.</author>
                  <author>Saint-Réal, M. l'abbé de (César Vichard), 1639-1692.</author>
                  <author>Porter, P.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>130, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by William Cademan,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation attributed to César Vichard de Saint-Réal--Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mazarin, Hortense Mancini, --  duchesse de, 1646-1699.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688.</term>
               <term>France --  Politics and government --  1643-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:45280:1"/>
            <p>Licenſed, February 22th. 1676.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Henry Oldenburg.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45280:1"/>
            <p>THE MEMOIRES OF THE DUTCHESS Mazarine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Out of French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>William Cademan,</hi> at the <hi>Popes-Head</hi> in the <hi>New-Exchange,</hi> and <hi>Middle-Exchange</hi> in the <hi>Strande,</hi> 1676.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:45280:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45280:2"/>
            <head>THE <hi>MEMOIRES</hi> OF THE Dutcheſs <hi>Mazarin.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince the Obligations I owe you are of that Nature, that I ought to conceal nothing from you, wherein I can teſtifie my Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments of them, I am willing to gratifie you with the true Relation of my Life, being you deſire it: Not that I am ignorant, how hard it is to ſpeak diſcreetly of one's ſelf. And you know how averſe I am in my Nature, from explaining to the World, matters wherein I am ſo neerly concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45280:3"/>yet it is very Natural to defend one's ſelf from Calumny; and to make appear, to thoſe, of whom we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived conſiderable Services, that we are not ſo unworthy of their Favours, as the traducing World would make us ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be: Nor can I ſpend the time of my Solitary Retreat, with more Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence. But if what I am going to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you with, ſeem to favour much of the <hi>Romance,</hi> impute it rather to my Deſtiny, than to my Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>I know the chief Glory of a Woman ought to conſiſt, in not making her ſelf to be publickly talked of. And thoſe that know me, know like-wiſe that I never took much pleaſure in things that make too much Noiſe. But it is not alwayes in our choiſe to live our own way: And there is a kind of Fatality, even in thoſe things that ſeem to depend upon the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt Conduct. I would not trouble you with the account of my Birth, if thoſe that envied my Uncles Glory, had not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to tarniſh the Luſtre thereof: But ſince their Fury ſpared nothing that was his, It is lawful for me, to let you know that <hi>I</hi> am deſcended from one of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45280:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>the moſt Illuſtrious Families of <hi>Rome;</hi> and that my Anceſtors theſe three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years have held a Rank ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and conſiderable, that <hi>I</hi> might paſs my dayes happily, though <hi>I</hi> had never been Heireſſe to a firſt Miniſter of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Accademy</hi> of Good Witts which began in that Country, at the Nuptials of one of our Family, made it appear in what eſteem that Houſe was in, at that time: And as a farther addition of Happineſs, <hi>I</hi> had the advantage to be deſcended from a Father, that was one of the moſt accompliſhed and beſt qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified of our Family. <hi>I</hi> was but ſix years old when <hi>I</hi> was brought into <hi>France;</hi> and a few years after <hi>Monſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eur M.</hi> rejected the Marriage of my Siſter, (<hi>afterwards marryed to the Conſtable of</hi> Collonna) and conceived ſuch a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Paſſion for me that upon a time he told Madam <hi>D' Eguillon;</hi> that if he could but have the happineſs to be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed to me, it would not grieve him to dye three Months after. The ſucceſs ſurpaſſed his deſire, he has married me; and yet, God be thanked, he is alive ſtill. Upon the firſt report of his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45280:4"/>refuſing my Siſter, the Cardinal was much offended; and would often ſay, He had rather marry me to a Serving-man. But he was not the only man <hi>I</hi> had the ill Fortune to pleaſe. An <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> Eunuch, Muſician to the Cardinal, was accuſed, for having a Kindneſs for me: But the truth is, That it was as much for my Siſter as for me. He was alſo jeered for being in love with the beautiful Statues that were in the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace <hi>M.</hi> This man's Love certainly was unlucky, ſince thoſe poor Statues were ſo cruelly puniſhed for it, as well as <hi>I,</hi> though they were as little in fault. It was no fault of my Siſters, that <hi>I</hi> was not in love with ſomething, as well as <hi>I</hi> was beloved. As ſhe had a ſincere Inclination for the King, ſhe would have been glad to ſee me ingaged with ſome ſuch Folly. But, being extream young and childiſh, <hi>I</hi> could fix to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. All that ſhe could obtain from me, to oblige her, was to ſhew ſome Complaſance to thoſe of my Age, that diverted me moſt, in our little Play-games, which then took up all my time and thoughts; though they were often interrupted by the King's Preſence;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45280:4"/>who ſeldom ſtirred from our Houſe; though he converſed amongſt us with wonderful goodneſs. He had ſo much of Serious and ſolid, (not to ſay of Majeſty) in all his wayes, that he could not keep himſelf from ſtriking through us, a moſt aweful Reſpect, even beyond his intentions. My Siſter was no way diſturbed at his Preſence, who ever elſe was. And you may eaſily conceive that his Aſſiduity had Charms for thoſe who were cauſe he had none for others. As the things which Paſſion makes us do, ſeem ridiculous to thoſe that have never known what that paſſion is. My Siſters, expoſed her very often to our Rallery. One time amongſt the reſt, we Jeered her, becauſe ſhe, ſeeing at a a diſtance, a Gentleman of the Houſe, who was about the King's Stature, with his back to her, ran to him with open arms, crying, <hi>Ha my poor Sire!</hi> An o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing that made us Sport about that time, was a Pleaſantry of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, with Madam <hi>de Bouillon,</hi> which was about ſix years old. The Court was then at <hi>Lafere.</hi> One day as he made ſport with her about ſome Gallant that he ſaid ſhe had: at laſt he began to chide
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45280:5"/>her, for being with Child. The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment which ſhe ſhewed, diverted all ſo, that it was agreed ſhe ſhould be ſtill told of it. They ſtreightened her Cloaths from time to time; and they made her believe that ſhe was growing very big.</p>
            <p>This continued as long as it was thought neceſſary, to perſwade her, to the likely-hood of her being with Child. Yet ſhe would never believe any thing of it, and denyed it with a great deal of heat, until the time of her Lying-in came, ſhe found betwixt her Sheets, in the morning, a Child new born. You cannot imagine the Aſtoniſhment and Grief ſhe was in, at this ſight. <hi>Such a thing,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver happned to any, but to the Virgin</hi> Mary <hi>and my ſelf; for I never felt any kind of Pain.</hi> The Queen came to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dole with her, and offered to be God-mother; many came to Goſſip with her, as newly brought to bed: And that which at firſt was but a Paſt-time, within doors, came to be the publick Divertiſment of all the Court. They preſſed her hard to tell who was the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but all they could get from her,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45280:5"/>was only, <hi>That it could be none but the King, or the Count of</hi> Guich, <hi>becauſe no other man but thoſe two had ever kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For my part, being three years el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der than her, <hi>I</hi> was infinitely proud that <hi>I</hi> knew the truth of the matter; and <hi>I</hi> could never be weary of laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to make people take notice that <hi>I</hi> knew it. You will hardly believe, that at thoſe years, when there is nothing leſs thought of, than of reaſoning upon things, <hi>I</hi> ſhould make as ſerious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexions, as <hi>I</hi> ever did of any thing of this Life. It is true, notwithſtanding, that my greateſt Delight was at that time, to ſhut my ſelf up alone, to write what-ever came into my head. <hi>It</hi> is not long ſince, ſome of thoſe Papers fell into my hands: And <hi>I</hi> do aſſure you, <hi>I</hi> was ſtrangely ſurprized to find things ſo far ſurpaſſing the Capacity of a little Girle. They were Doubts and Queſtions which <hi>I</hi> propoſed to my ſelf, upon all things, which gave me trouble to comprehend. <hi>I</hi> could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſufficiently ſatisfie my Fancy in deciding them: But ſtill <hi>I</hi> ſought with Obſtinacy, what <hi>I</hi> could not dive into,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45280:6"/>nor find. And if in my Conduct ſince, <hi>I</hi> have not ſhewed much, <hi>I</hi> have at leaſt this Conſolation, that <hi>I</hi> had a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great deſire to attain to good Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>I</hi> remember about that time, writing to a young Lady, for whom <hi>I</hi> had a great kindneſs; <hi>I</hi> began to grow weary of writing ſo often, <hi>I love you,</hi> in one and the ſame Letter; and gave her to underſtand, that here-after <hi>I</hi> would only make a Croſs to ſignifie theſe three Words. Following this new invention, it happened ſome times that <hi>I</hi> writ to this Lady, letters where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there was nothing elſe to be ſeen but whole lines of Croſſes, one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. One of theſe Letters fell after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards into the hands of ſome, whom it concerned to find out the Myſtery; but could never find fault with ſo God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Cypher. My Enfancy being paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed amongſt theſe innocent Amuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or Paſt-times, they began to talk of a Match for me. Fortune, that intended to make me the unhappieſt Woman living, began to flatter me, with the ſhew of making me a Queen; and had like to have render'd the man, ſhe deſtined for me, moſt odious to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45280:6"/>me, by the compariſon of thoſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhe firſt did cajole my Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Yet <hi>I</hi> can truly ſay for my ſelf, that thoſe Illuſtrious Matches never dazled my fancy. And Monſieur <hi>M.</hi> dares not ſay, that he ever found me guilty of any Vain-glory, above my condition. All the World knows how many repeated Treaties were on foot, to Match me with a great Potentate. As for the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> you know what has been ſaid in the Journey to <hi>Lyons,</hi> and that that Affair was broken off, upon the Cardinal's obſtinate refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, to abandon <hi>Geneva,</hi> in conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Marriage. We lodged at <hi>Bell-Court;</hi> and our Chamber Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, which open'd towards the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-place,</hi> were low enough for one to get in with eaſe. Madam <hi>de Venel</hi> our Governeſs was ſo uſed to her trade of over-looking us, that ſhe roſe even in her ſleep, to ſee what we were doing. One night as my Siſter lay aſleep with her mouth open, Madam <hi>de Venell,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her accuſtomed manner, coming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep as ſhe was, to grope in the dark, happen'd to thruſt her finger into her mouth, ſo far, that my Siſter ſtarting
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45280:7"/>out of her ſleep, made her Teeth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt meet in her Finger. Judg you the Amazement they both were in to find themſelves in this poſture, when they were throughly awake. My Siſter was in a grievous fret. The Story was told the King the next day; and the Court had the Divertiſment of laughing at it.</p>
            <p>The Cardinal, whether it were through Modeſty or Diſſimulation ſhewed himſelf as averſe, as the Queen to the Kings purſuit of my Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as the Marriage with <hi>Spaine</hi> was concluded, nothing was ſo much in his thoughts as how handſomly to ſend her further off, fearing leſt ſhe might be a hindrance to it; a litle af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our return from <hi>Lyons</hi> he ſent us to ſtay for him at <hi>Fountain-bleau;</hi> from thence he carried us to <hi>Pontois,</hi> where he left it to her Choice, to retire, to what placed ſhe pleaſed, ſhe Choſe <hi>Rochelle:</hi> The Cardinal willing to wean her a litle more, made Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Frejus</hi> at <hi>Brouage,</hi> to propoſe to her the Marriage of the Conſtable <hi>Collonna.</hi> but ſhe rejected it; her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45280:7"/>being not yet drawn into <hi>Italy</hi> by what drew her thither ſince. He had reſolved to carry Madam <hi>de Bouillon</hi> and me to the Marriage; But my Siſter obſtinately refuſing to let us go, when he ſent for us, unleſs ſhe might go too; he choſe rather to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive himſelf of the Pleaſure of ſeeing us there, than to let her come with us. At their return from the <hi>Frontiers,</hi> we were ſent for to <hi>Fountain-bleau,</hi> where the Court then was. The King looked but coldly upon my Siſter; and his Change began to make her reſolve to marry into <hi>Italy.</hi> She would often pray me to tell her as many ill things of the King as <hi>I</hi> could. But beſides; that it was hard to ſpeak ill of ſuch a Prince as he, who lived amongſt us with that Familiarity and charming Sweetneſs; <hi>I</hi> being but ten years old then, <hi>I</hi> could not well comprehend what it was ſhe would have; all <hi>I</hi> could do for her, Loving her tenderly, and ſeeing her all in Teares, was to weep for her Misfortunes with her, until ſhe might, at my turn, bear me Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany to weep mine. The Averſion the Cardinal had for her fondneſs to the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45280:8"/>King, made him conceive a great un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs for her; and as this intrigue began with her firſt coming into the World, it may be ſaid, that he hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ever loved her. My Brother's Humour was nothing more pleaſing to him, and his Conduct muchleſs; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially ſince he was accuſed to have been of the Debauch of <hi>Roiſſi.</hi> One of the things which moſt diſpleaſed him in us, was the want of Devotion; you cannot imagine how much he was diſcontented at it. He ſeft no Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments untried, to induce us to have more. On a time complaining that we did not frequent the Church eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day; he ſaid, We had neither Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty nor Honour: <hi>At leaſt,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>If you will not do it for God</hi>'s <hi>ſake, do it for the Worlds ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though <hi>I</hi> was as much concerned in his Remonſtrances, as the reſt; yet either becauſe I was the youngeſt, and ſo the leſs faulty; or that he ſaw ſomething in my humour that pleaſed him better, He had for along time as much tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for me, as he had averſion for them; which made him to chuſe me, to leave his Eſtate and Name, to the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45280:8"/>man he ſhould wed me to; which like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe made him more Circumſpect in the care of my Education, than of the reſt, and at laſt alſo diſpleaſed when he believed I had given him cauſe. He was very apprehenſive of my ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Affections to any one; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de Vennel,</hi> who had directions to pry into all my Actions, would be continually ſpeaking to me of every one that came to viſit me, or were likely to ingage my love, to diſcover by my Diſcourſe my Thoughts of every Body; but I having no tie more to one than to another, ſhe could never make any Diſcovery, and ſhe had been in Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance to this hour had not the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcretion of my Siſter made her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what was not. I told you that ſhe would always preſs me to love ſomthing. She importuned me for ſome Years to tell her if none of the Court pleaſed me more than another; at laſt being over come with her intreaties, I told her, I ſaw a Youth in the houſe, that I liked above the reſt, but that <hi>I</hi> ſhould be very ſorry he ſhould be half ſo pleaſing in my Eye as the King was in hers. Over joyed to have drawn
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45280:9"/>this Confeſſion from me, ſhe asked me his Name, but <hi>I</hi> knew it not. And though ſhe took all the paines imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to make me deſcribe him, ſhe was above two moneth vexing of me before ſhe could find him out. She underſtood at laſt that it was an <hi>Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Gentleman newly come from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Page of the great Chamber who was then but one of the ſub-Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants in the Guards, but has been ſince Killed in a higher employment in <hi>Flanders.</hi> She told me his Name, and likewiſe made her ſelf merry with the King about my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended inclinations, from whom ſhe could conceal nothing. The Cardinal knew it a little after, and believeing it quite another thing than it really was, ſpoke to me of it in very harſh terms. It was the right way to make ſomthing of nothing; and if <hi>I</hi> were capable of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gageing my ſelf for ſpight, his repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches might incline me to deſerve them. As this Gentleman was familiar in the Houſe, the Noiſe the Cardinal made about it, reached his Ear, and raiſed in him Thoughts which he perhaps ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had before; at length he found
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45280:9"/>means to make them known to me, and by my Siſters good will <hi>I</hi> ſhould have anſwred his Paſſion, inſtead of deſpiſing and rejecting it. In the mean time the Cardinals Diſtemper grew every day worſe and worſe, the deſire he had to Eternize his Name, carried him above the indignation he had conceived againſt me. He broke his Mind to the Biſhop of <hi>Frejus,</hi> and deſired to know his Opinion of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Perſons, and which of them he thought propereſt for me. This Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop won before by Monſieur <hi>M.</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on promiſe of fifty thouſand Crowns, forgot nothing that might deſerve them; but he never had them: For he returned the Bond which was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, intimating, <hi>He had a greater mind to the Biſhoprick of</hi> Eureux <hi>if it could be gotten for him.</hi> But the King having diſpoſed of it to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, notwithſtanding Monſieur <hi>M.</hi> his ſoliciting for the ſpace of two moneths. Monſieur <hi>Frejus</hi> deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the fifty thouſand Crowns, but Monſieur <hi>M.</hi> was no longer in the mind to Pay them. As ſoon as the marriage was concluded, he ſent me
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45280:10"/>a great, Cabinet wherein amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Rich things, there was ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Piſtols in Gold. <hi>I</hi> gave great part of this gold to my Brother and Siſters, to leſſen their hatred of my Opulencies, which they could not ſee without Envy, what ever meen they made. <hi>I</hi> never put them to the trouble of asking me, for the Key was always in the Cabinet, and who would, might take, for me. One day wanting other divertiſement, we threw above three Hundred Piſtols out at the Windows of the Pallace <hi>Mazarine;</hi> to have the pleaſure of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Company of Servants that were in the Court to ſcramble and fight for them. This Prodigallity being told the Cardinal, it cauſed ſo much Diſpleaſure in him, that it is believed it haſtned his end; but whether it were ſo or no, he died within eight days after, and left me the Richeſt Heireſs, but the unhappieſt Woman, in all Chriſtendome. Upon the firſt Tidings of his Death, my Brother and my Siſter, inſtead of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſorry, Cryed to one another, God be thanked he is gon. And to tell
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45280:10"/>you the Truth, <hi>I</hi> was not much more afflicted; and it is a remarkable thing, that a man of that merit that all his Life had laboured to raiſe, and enrich his Family, ſhould never receive o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Thanks from them, than appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſigns of hatred and averſion even after his Death.</p>
            <p>But if you knew with what ſeverity he treated us, you would be leſs ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at this. Never man had ſo ſweet a behaviour abroad and in publick, and ſo harſh and ſevere at home, all our humours and inclinations were point blank oppoſite to his. Add to this the Tyrannical Subjection we were kept in. The tenderneſs of our years, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibility and careleſneſs we had for all things, to which to much plenty; &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity reduces moſt Perſons of this Age, in ſpite of all their good Nature.</p>
            <p>For my own particular, Fortune has taken Care to puniſh my Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude by thoſe misfortunes, which have continually followed me, one in the Neck of another, ever ſince his Death: <hi>I</hi> know not what fore-know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my Siſter had of them; but upon the firſt Diſcontents vvhich <hi>I</hi> fell
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45280:11"/>into after my Marriage, ſhe told me by way of Conſolation, <hi>Go, go, you will yet be more unhappy than I.</hi> Monſieur <hi>de Lorraine</hi> vvho for a long time vvas paſſionatly in Love vvith her, made uſe of all his Rethorick to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade her to marry Him, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued his purſuite even after the Cardinals Death. The Queen Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, vvho vvould by no means have her ſtay in <hi>France,</hi> charged Madam <hi>de Vennel</hi> to break off this Intreague at any rate. But all their Endeavours had been fruitleſs, had they not been ſeconded by certain Reaſons unknown to all the World.</p>
            <p>And though the King had the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſity to give her, her Choyce of any man elſe in <hi>France,</hi> if ſhe could not fancy Monſieur <hi>de Loraine,</hi> and that he ſeemed to be ſenſibly diſpleaſed at her reſolution to go out of <hi>France,</hi> her evil Stars Drew her into <hi>Italy</hi> againſt all Reaſon.</p>
            <p>The Conſtable who at firſt belei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that the Amours of Kings could not be innocent, was ſo much tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45280:11"/>with joy to find the contrary in the perſon of my Siſter, that he made litle account of not being the firſt that had gain'd her heart; he left his bad Opinion that he had, which all <hi>Italians</hi> have, of the liberty which Ladies have in <hi>France</hi> and made her live with the ſame freedom in <hi>Rome,</hi> ſince he found ſhe uſed it ſo diſcreetly. In the mean time the <hi>Eunuch</hi> her Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, who now by his abſence, and the Cardinals Death, Lived without Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, undertook to make himſelf neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary about me; but beſides that, my my own Nature made me a ſtranger to to all ſorts of intregues Monſieur <hi>M.</hi> Kept too ſtrict an Eye over all my Actions. He enraged at this Obſtacle, took a Reſolution to be Revenged of Monſieur <hi>M.</hi> himſelf.</p>
            <p>This man kept his acceſs to the King with the ſame freedome he enjoyed when he vvas my Siſters Confident. He makes a great Complaint to him of the Severity Monſieur <hi>M.</hi> uſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me, <hi>That he was obliged to take my part as having been the Cardinals Creature and my particular Servant. That Monſieur</hi> Mazarine <hi>was jealous
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:45280:12"/>of all the World. And above all of his Majeſty; and he cauſed me to be watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed very narrowly in all places where the King</hi> (vvho had no thoughts of me) <hi>might ſee me, and that beſides, he took upon Him, as if he were a great Miniſter, and that he Threatned to baniſh all the</hi> Italians <hi>out of</hi> Paris.</p>
            <p>To all this, the King only anſwered, <hi>That if what he ſaid was true, the Duke of</hi> Mazarine <hi>was a Fool, and that though He had inherited Cardinal</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarines <hi>VVealth, he had not his Power;</hi> All that was true of this Report, was only that Monſieur <hi>Mazarine,</hi> being informed of this Eunuques intregues, threatned to put him out of the Pallace of <hi>Mazarine</hi> where he had Lodgings. Not content with what he had done, he was ſo unwiſe as to boaſt of it before a Lady of Quality of Province called Madam <hi>de Ruz,</hi> who was I know not how acquainted with Monſieur <hi>Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine,</hi> ſhe tells him of the ill Office that had been done him. He had a mind to place about me ſome Lady, who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Name of Governant might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the function; and finding this Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de Ruz</hi> very proper to act this Part,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45280:12"/>he made Choice of her, as an acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the Intelligence ſhe gave him; He prayes her to find out ſome means to get her ſelf preſented to me without letting me know that he was acquainted with her; Monſieur <hi>de Frejus</hi> ſpake to me of her as from himſelf ſometime af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards; and brought her to me up a paire of back Staires, one day when Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> was a Hunting. I was much taken with her, and as I knew, that if it were perceived that I liked her, <hi>I</hi> ſhould not be permitted to have her; I was not willing any of the houſe ſhould ſee her before ſhe were received into my Family. One day, as <hi>I</hi> was alone with her, Madam <hi>de Vennel</hi> came ſuddainly into the Room, and broke a busk we had ſet to bar the Dore, and ſhut our ſelves in. Of a ſuddain Madam <hi>de Ruz,</hi> with a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Preſence of Wit, began to roul her Eyes in her head, to Weep, and Cry with the Tone of a Beggar, <hi>that ſhe was a poor Gentlewoman of</hi> Loraine, <hi>and prayed me to take Compaſſion of her mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</hi> As ſhe had the Ayr of her Face extream Brisk and Lively, as moſt of the Provincialls have, her Grimaſle
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45280:13"/>ſucceeded ſo well, and ſo diſguiſed her, that <hi>I</hi> my ſelf could hardly know her again. Madam <hi>de Vennel</hi> was ſo terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly affrighted at her, that ſhe run as far off from her as ſhe could, and told all about ſince, <hi>that ſhe found the Devil in my Chamber.</hi> Monſieur <hi>Mazarine's</hi> Cunning Artifice in the Choice of this Woman, in a ſeaſon wherein he could not yet have any Subject to Complain of any of my Actions, may ſuffice to inſtruct you with his natural Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and in what diſpoſition of mind he Married me. As he apprehended my abode in <hi>Paris,</hi> he continually marched me about to his Lord - ſhips, and Governments; during the firſt three or four Years of our Marriage, <hi>I</hi> made three Journies into <hi>Alſatia,</hi> and as many into <hi>Brittany,</hi> beſides ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral others to <hi>Nevers, Maine, Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon, Sedan,</hi> and other places. Have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no greater delight in <hi>Paris,</hi> but the pleaſure of ſeeing him, it was not ſo irkſome to me, as it might be to a Perſon of my Age to be deprived of the divertiſements of the Court. And perhaps <hi>I</hi> ſhould never have been ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with this wandering kind of Life,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45280:13"/>if he had not too much abuſed my Complacency. He has often made me travel two hundred Leagues when <hi>I</hi> was big with Child, and very near my time; my Relations and Friends were apprehenſive of the Dangers to which he Expoſed my Health, &amp; endeavoured to make me ſenſible of them, but it was along time in vain; VVhat would they ſay, If they had known that <hi>I</hi> could not once ſpeak to any of my Domeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks but they were turned away the next day? That <hi>I</hi> could not receive two Viſits fucceſſively from any one man but he was preſently forbid the Houſe; and if <hi>I</hi> ſhewed more kindneſs for any of my Maids more than for the reſt, ſhe was immediately taken away from me. If <hi>I</hi> called for my Coach, and he thought it not conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to let me go abroad, he would laughing forbid the Coach to be made ready, and then would Droll upon it ſo long till the hour was paſt to go where <hi>I</hi> deſigned. He would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that <hi>I</hi> ſhould ſee none in the world but himſelf. Above all, he could not endure that <hi>I</hi> ſhould ſee his Kindred, nor mine own; mine, becauſe they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45280:14"/>to take my part; his own, becauſe they did no more approve of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct than mine did.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> was a long time Lodged at the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenal</hi> with Madam <hi>de Oradous</hi> his Couſin, without ever being permitted ſee her. The Innocence of my Recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations, which were capable to put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man elſe of his Humour out of doubt, who had reſerved any Regard for my Age, gave him as much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet as if they had been very Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. Some times he ſaid, It was a ſin to play with my Servants at Cock — all At other times he ſaid, It was a haynous Crime to go to Bed Late. Once when Monſieur <hi>Colbert,</hi> deſired to know all his Grievances, and Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Complaint againſt me, he could never alledge any other than theſe two; He often ſayd, One could not in Conſcience go to Court, and much leſs to Plays; ſomtimes my Devotions were too ſhort: In fine, his Peeviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs upon my account was ſuch, that <hi>I</hi> verily believe, if any one would ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly ask him how, and after what ſort he would have me live, that he could not agree with himſelf about
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45280:14"/>the manner. He ought indeed to have ſaid, <hi>That Knowing of what value I was, he could not be too ſolicitous of me; That the Converſation of the World being ſo Contagious, what ever Sport or Ralleries was made of him, he would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to hinder my being ſpoiled, becauſe he loved me more than his own proper Reputation.</hi> But if it was his love for me, that made him Treat me after this fantaſtical Faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it were to be wiſhed for, for both our quiets, that he had honoured me with a little more of his indifference. No ſooner did he perceive that <hi>I</hi> took de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in any place, but <hi>I</hi> was immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately hurried from thence, though there were never ſo great a reaſon for my ſtay there. We were at <hi>Maine</hi> when the News was brought of the Journey to <hi>Marſal;</hi> he had Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to be there, and ſent me into <hi>Brittaine</hi> to keep Company with his Father, who was at the meeting of the States there, while he was preparing himſelf at <hi>Paris</hi> for his Journey; he had intelligence from ſome of his Spies, (by whom <hi>I</hi> was continually beſet and watched) that <hi>I</hi> paſſed my
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45280:15"/>time there very pleaſantly; he fell ſick upon it, and ſent for me away with all ſpeed. His Father underſtanding that his Phyſitians adviſed him to go to the VVaters of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> would not let me go, alleadging, <hi>That a Man while he Drank thoſe VVaters muſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from VVomen.</hi> Upon this News he fell into a Swoun for vexation, and after ſeveral Couriers ſent for me, his Father at laſt let me go; <hi>I</hi> went with him to <hi>Bourbon,</hi> where <hi>I</hi> remained a moneth ſhut up with him in a Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, to ſee him ſpue up his Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, without ſo much as viſiting Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam the Princeſs, who was there, and to whom he had the Honor to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated. He could not preſently be induced to believe that it was his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that kept me from departing out of <hi>Britany;</hi> and notwithſtanding all the aſſurance he receaved of it ſince, He maintained always, that I had been better pleaſed to paſs my time there, than come and ſolace him in his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. It had not been hard for me to juſtifie my ſelf, if he would but hear me. But that he avoided ſtill the moſt he could, becauſe all the blame
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:45280:15"/>would be found of his ſide in the clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the matter, and he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver acknowledg himſelf in an Errour: nothing afflicted me more than his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion to be Informed or Convinced of a miſtake, becauſe he took upon him the juriſdiction of treating me continually as guilty. Some time after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards being obliged for the Kings Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to go into <hi>Brittaine,</hi> he took ſuch an obſtinate Reſolution to have me with him, and writ ſuch ſtrange things upon this occaſion to the <hi>Abbot de Effiat</hi> his near kinſman, that <hi>I</hi> was forced to go from <hi>Paris</hi> three weeks after <hi>I</hi> was brought to Bed. Few VVomen of my Quality would have done the like; but what would not one do for the enjoying of ſo great a good, as Peace? And to mend the matter, he made me lodg in one of the wretchedeſt Villages in all that Country, and in ſo miſerable a Cottage, that we were conſtrained to be out of dores all day. He always made Choiſe of ſuch places becauſe <hi>I</hi> ſhould ſee no Company, alſo far from ſeeing any of the people of thoſe Villages: thoſe whoſe civility or buſineſs brought thither to ſee him,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45280:16"/>were forced to lie in the Fields for want of Inns; and if they diſpleaſed him never ſo little, he ſent them of Errands, about ſeveral buſineſſes which depended upon him in this Province. Yet we ſpent ſix months in this plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant place, in the year 1666. Another time being alone, at <hi>Bourbon,</hi> having ſent me into <hi>Britain,</hi> he underſtood by his Spies that I diverted my ſelf very pleaſantly with <hi>Madam de Coaquin,</hi> and that few days paſſed but we appointed to take the Aire either at Land or by Sea: His wonted diſquiet ſeizing him, he ſends for me to meet him at <hi>Nevers, where,</hi> as he ſaid, <hi>there were very good Comedians amongſt other divertiſements.</hi> I began to be weary of making ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny idle Journeys, I writ to Monſieur <hi>Colbert</hi> to complain; but being adviſed by him to go, I was much ſurpriſed to find Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> upon the Road ten Leagues from <hi>Nevers,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Paris</hi> with my Brother who was returning out of <hi>Italy.</hi> He would never give me any Reaſon why he dealt ſo ſtrangly with me; we went without any farther clearing of this doubt, to confine our ſelves at our
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:45280:16"/>
               <hi>Caſſine,</hi> near <hi>Sedan,</hi> whither my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, out of Complaiſance, ſeeing me very melancholly, accompanied us. It was there firſt that Monſieur <hi>Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin</hi> made ſhew as if he were Jealous of him, not knowing otherwiſe how to be rid of him; &amp; being unwilling to have ſuch a witneſs of his domeſtick pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, you may judge of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment for ſo baſe and wicked a ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion; but if all theſe out rages, by hearing them related, ſeem hard to be indured, the manner with which he did them, was yet ſomething more cruel &amp; barbarous. I will give you one ſcant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, by which you ſhall judge of the reſt: Being one Night with the Queen, I ſaw him coming towards me ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pleaſant, and with a conſtrained and affected Smile publiquely made me this Complement. <hi>Madam, I have good Newes to tell you, the King has juſt now Commanded me to go into</hi> Alſatia. Monſieur <hi>de Roque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laure</hi> who was then preſent, moved, as well as the reſt of the Company, with this ſilly Affectation, but more frank than the reſt, could not refrain telling him, <hi>That this was
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:45280:17"/>fine Newes indeed to be told with ſo much Joy to a woman of my Condition.</hi> But Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> diſdaining to reply, went quietly out of the Room very proud of his Gallantry. The King hearing of it, was moved to pitty. He took the paines to tell me himſelf, that my ſtay there ſhould be only for three months, and kept his word with me, as he always did.</p>
            <p>If <hi>I</hi> did not apprehend to tyre your Patience, <hi>I</hi> could tell you a thouſand ſuch little malitious tricks which he playd me, without any manner of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, out of the meer pleaſure he took to torment me. Fancy then to your ſelf, continual oppoſitions to my moſt innocent deſires; and an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable hatiled againſt all thoſe <hi>I</hi> lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, or loved me; an undeſatigable care to bring into my preſence all thoſe <hi>I</hi> hated mortally, and to corrupt thoſe of my Servants whom <hi>I</hi> moſt truſted, to betray my Secrets if <hi>I</hi> had any; a ſtudious Application to cry the down every where, and make my Actions odious to all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. In fine, all that the Malignity of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:45280:17"/>the by - got Cabal could invent or practiſe, in a houſe where it had abſolute Tyranny, againſt a ſimple young Woman, careleſs, and whoſe want of circumſpection in her Actions, gave every day new matter to her Enemies to inſult over her. I boldly make uſe of this expreſſion, <hi>By - got Cabal,</hi> becauſe I cannot think that <hi>I</hi> erre againſt the moſt ſtrict Rules of Chriſtianity, when <hi>I</hi> preſume that thoſe Devotes by whoſe directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> doth Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late his Actions, are not truly ſo, having promoted the Diſſipation of ſo many Millions.</p>
            <p>And this is the fatal Article that has made me loſe all patience, and that has been the true beginning of all my misfortunes. If Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> had only taken delight in overwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming me with ſadneſs and grief, and in expoſing my Health and my Life to his moſt unreaſonable caprice; and in making me paſs my beſt days in an unparalled ſlavery, ſince Heaven has been pleaſed to make him my Maſter; I ſhould have endeavoured to allay and qualifie my misfortunes by my
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:45280:18"/>Sighs and Tears, and my complaints to my particular Friends: But when <hi>I</hi> ſaw, that by his incredible Dilapida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and profuſeneſs, my ſon, who might have been the Richeſt Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in <hi>France,</hi> was in danger of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the pooreſt; there was no reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the force of Nature, and mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Love carried it over all other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations of Duty, or the moderation <hi>I</hi> propoſed to my ſelf. <hi>I</hi> ſaw every day vaſt ſumms go away; movables of ineſtimable price, Offices, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and all the Rich remaines of my Unkles Fortune, the Fruits of his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and the Rewards of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices; I ſaw as much ſold as came to three Millions before <hi>I</hi> took any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick notice of it. And <hi>I</hi> had hardly any thing left me of Value, but my Jewels; when Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> took an occaſion to ſeize upon them, He took his opportunity to lay hold of them, one Night as <hi>I</hi> came late home from the City. Deſiring to know the Reaſon of this Proceeding, before <hi>I</hi> went to bed, he told me, <hi>That I being of a free and liberal Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, he was afraid I ſhould give away
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:45280:18"/>ſome of them, and that he had not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them from me, but with intention to return them again with the addition of others.</hi> I anſwered him, <hi>that it were to be wiſhed his liberality had been as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular as mine, that I was ſatisfied with them I had already, and that I would not go to bed until I had them again.</hi> And ſeeing that to what ever I could ſay, he only replied with unpleaſant Ralleries, expreſſed with a malicious Laugh, or a ſcorning calmneſs of Voice, but in reallity moſt tart and bitter, I went out of the Room all in Deſpaire, and paſſed to my Brothers Pallace, extreamly perplexed, not knowing what courſe to take.</p>
            <p>Madam <hi>de Bouillon</hi> whom we Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſent for, having heard this my new occaſion of complaint, told me <hi>I</hi> was well enough ſerved, ſince <hi>I</hi> had ſuffered ſo much already without ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Word. I reſolved to have gon away with her in that very inſtant, if Madam <hi>de Belinzani</hi> whom we like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſent for, had not hindred me, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating me to ſtay until ſhe had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to Monſieur <hi>Mazarine.</hi> But he had given order that none ſhould be
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:45280:19"/>admitted; yet Madam <hi>de Belinzani</hi> through much obſtinate preſſing was ſuffered to come unto him, but would not give her leave to ſpeak, nor could ſhe get any other Anſwer, <hi>but that her buſineſs, could not be ſo urgent with him, as to oblige her to come at ſo unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable an hour; but that if ſhe had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing to ſay to him, he was going next morning to St.</hi> Germain, <hi>and he would give her a meeting at the Croſs of Nantare.</hi> Madam <hi>de Belinzani</hi> being returned as ill ſatisfied, as we, at ſo unreaſonable a Rallary; it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded <hi>I</hi> ſhould go to lie at Madam <hi>de Bouillions,</hi> the next day all my Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being come thither about my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, Madam the Counteſs was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to acquaint the King with it. He received her very Graciouſly. And Madam the Princeſs of <hi>Carignan</hi> was Commanded to come and carry me with her to the <hi>Hotel</hi> of <hi>Soiſſon;</hi> after ſtaying there about two months I was obliged to return with Monſieur <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarine,</hi> even without having my Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els reſtored to me, or with any other ſatisfaction, but to be allowed to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge ſome Women which he placed
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:45280:19"/>about me whom I did not like, that was the only Favour I could obtain. When <hi>I</hi> preſſed to have my Jewels reſtored, Madam the Counteſs was the firſt that told me <hi>I</hi> did very ill. The Court was always againſt me e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince that time. It is well known of what Conſequence that is in all manner of buſineſs. <hi>I</hi> told the King in theſe Termes, <hi>That I ſhould Comfort my ſelf to ſee</hi> Monſieur <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarin ſo much favour'd againſt me, if he were ſo in all other things, and if the litle help he found in his other affairs did not make it appeare that he had no other friends, but my Enemies.</hi> As this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord was rather a triumph for him than a real accomodation, it made him too haughty, to let it be of any long continuance. An hour before my going to the Pallace <hi>Mazarine I</hi> ſent thither a Groom of the Chamber, whom Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam the Counteſs had prefered to me ſince my coming thither, with ſome of my things. Monſieur <hi>Mazarine,</hi> that knew him as well as <hi>I</hi> did, having asked him what he would have, or who he belonged to; bad him be gon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his buſieſs, without letting him ſtay until I came.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:45280:20"/>
            <p>This poor fellow met me about two hundred paces from my Houſe, and told me what happned; and though Madam the Counteſs, who came to conduct me, perceived that this was a Juſt Cauſe of a new breach; ſhe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded me to paſs forward, and when ſhe had brought me to the ſtaire - foot, ſhe took her leave of me, being unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſee Monſieur <hi>Mazarine,</hi> becauſe he had uſed all his endeavours to have me removed to the Pallace of <hi>Conty,</hi> as if the <hi>Hotel</hi> of <hi>Soiſſon</hi> where ſhe lived, had not been as convenient, and as ſafe a place for me. <hi>I</hi> begun imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to beg that this Servant might be received again into my retinue, but all in vaine, although the neceſſity <hi>I</hi> ſaw my ſelf reduced to, by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Powers, made me ſhow ſubmiſſions beyond my natural inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But <hi>I</hi> had a man to deal with, that knew how to make uſe of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture. Seeing then that he payd me with bald Excuſes, and as bad Jeſts, <hi>I</hi> reſolved to leave him the ſecond time, and to withdraw my ſelf to my Brothers Houſe. But Monſieur <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine</hi> (as you ſhall perceive by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel)
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:45280:20"/>had taken a courſe that <hi>I</hi> ſhould not go out when <hi>I</hi> pleaſed, meaning to make me a Priſoner in my own houſe; ſeeing me offer to go, he threw himſelf in my way, and puſhed me ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rudely to ſtop my paſſage. But my Grief and Vexation ſupplying me with more than ordinary ſtrength, <hi>I</hi> thruſt by him in ſpight of all he could do; and though he called out to the Servants to ſhut all the Doors, and the Court - Gate eſpecially; they ſeeing me all in Tears, none durſt obey: I was fain to go round by the Street, (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there was a great throng of People) in this ſad condition; alone, a foot, and at noon-day, to get to my accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Sanctuary.</p>
            <p>This was the Effect of that Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that made him wall up the door, by which there was a Communication betwixt my Brother's Pallace and mine; and through which I made my eſcape the time before. But this pre-caution gave occaſion to all men that knew of it, to judge that he never intended me any better uſage for the future, (if I return'd again to him) than I had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore received at his hands; having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:45280:21"/>ſuch care to ſecure me for the time to-come.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as I came to my Brothers, I writ to the King, to give him an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of my proceeding: And Madam the <hi>Counteſſe</hi> carryed me with her to the Pallace of <hi>Soiſſons:</hi> But after five or ſix dayes Monſieur <hi>De Louvoy</hi> came to me from the King, to propoſe to me to retire into ſome Nunnery; but Madam the <hi>Counteſſe</hi> would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to that; but brought it about, that Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> ſhould be obliged to come and agree, and carry me home with him, upon condition that ſhe would be friends with him.</p>
            <p>Preſently after this, my Brother went away for <hi>Italy;</hi> partly to make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that he did not contribute any thing to a miſ-underſtanding betwixt Monſieur <hi>Mazarin</hi> and me; and that it ſhould not be his fault, if we did not live peaceably together. But I enjoyed but an out-ſide appearance of that Quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which I hoped to have: For, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all my Reſolutions of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, there paſſed not one day for three Months, that we continued to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, without ſome jarring, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of diſguſt.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:45280:21"/>
            <p>At the end of this time, he took a fancy to go into <hi>Alſatia;</hi> and inſtead of gratifying me, and obliging me with his Kindneſs to go (as I had reſolved to do) along with him: He was ſo ill adviſed, as to force me to entertain a Woman that I could no way approve of.</p>
            <p>This his Quarrel about a trifle, made me open my Eyes, and to think better of what courſe I was to take.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Friends had the goodneſs to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to me, the little Security I muſt hope for, from a man of that Caprice, in a place ſo Remote, and where his Power was ſo abſolute. That after what had paſſed betwixt us, I was a Fool to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine I ſhould ever be ſuffered to return from thence: That he had ſent my Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els before, for no other reaſon, but to confine himſelf for ever to that his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, where he ſhould not be obliged to give any account of his Conduct, as at</hi> Paris; <hi>and if ever I ſhould have need of my Friends, I ſhould be ſo far from them, that they could do me no other good, but unprofitably, to wiſh my Condition were better.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:45280:22"/>
            <p>Theſe Conſiderations, that were but too apparent, and too well grounded, made me take Sanctuary once more at Madam the <hi>Counteſſes,</hi> the night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> was to begin his Journey, fearing leſt he would have uſed Violence to have forced me along with him.</p>
            <p>I was ſo full of Perplexity and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction, to ſee my ſelf anew reduced to this Neceſſity, that I forgot to bring away my ſmall Jewels, which were left me, for my daily uſe; and might be worth about fifty thouſand Crowns; as they were the only Treaſure I had left; Madam the <hi>Counteſſe</hi> was ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident as to ask me for them, as ſoon as ſhe ſaw me: by that means I had time enough to ſend for them away. He came the next day to know what I meant: Anſwer was made him that I meant two things; the one, Not to go into <hi>Alſatia;</hi> the other, That he ſhould reſtore me my great Jewels, which he ſent before unto <hi>Alſatia,</hi> and which were the firſt cauſe of our Breach. For <hi>Alſatia</hi> he would have been contented to excuſe me, ſince he ſaw no great likely-hood of being able to perſwade
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:45280:22"/>me to it. But for my Jewels, he would make no peremptory anſwer; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as ſoon as ſhe left us, Madam the Princeſs of <hi>Baden</hi> carried me to Monſ. <hi>Colberts,</hi> to beſeech him to ſeize them into his own hands. He believed I ought not to be refuſed that Favour: They were forced to be brought back; and they have remained ever ſince in his hands.</p>
            <p>Now the Queſtion was, What ſhould become of me? Monſieur <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarine</hi> left me my Choice of going to live at the <hi>Hotel de Conty,</hi> or at <hi>Abbey</hi> of <hi>Chelles,</hi> the only two places in the World, he knew I hated mortally, and that for very juſt Reaſons. The Oppreſſion of Spirit under which I lay, would not give me leave to determine which I ſhould chuſe of thoſe two pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, equally odious to me: I was fain to let others chuſe for me; and the reaſons I had againſt the Pallace of <hi>Conty</hi> being more prevalent, the <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey</hi> of <hi>Chelles</hi> was preferred before that of <hi>Conty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here it was in this Solitude, that I had time to make Reflections upon the Duty, which my Friends told me was
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:45280:23"/>incumbent upon me, to deſire a Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Goods, in favour of my poor Children, before Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> had ſpent all; which at laſt I reſolved to do. Though I was convinced in my own Senſe, I ought to ſolicite it; yet the particular Reaſons I had to referre all this to, Monſieur <hi>Colbert</hi>'s Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whom I cauſed to be ſounded upon this matter; and finding him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe to it, put a ſtop to all.</p>
            <p>Some ſix months afterwards Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> coming out of <hi>Alſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> made me a Viſit as he paſſed that way; to oblige me to diſcharge two young women, which Madam the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe</hi> had given me ſince his departure for <hi>Alſatia.</hi> I did not believe my ſelf bound to ſatisfie his Deſires in this particular, being I knew it was for no other reaſon he deſired it, but out of his Animoſity againſt her. His Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Denial put him upon pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioning the King to have me remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from thence, to ſome other Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, upon I know not what pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texts. But the real Truth was, becauſe the Abbeſſe of <hi>Chelles,</hi> who was his Aunt, treated me civilly; and that I
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:45280:23"/>was well enough ſatisfied with my a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode there. He prevailed; and though that Abbeſſe was, as ſhe had cauſe, much offended; and gave as favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble an account of my behaviour there, as could be deſired. Yet Monſieur <hi>Le Premier</hi> came to tell me, <hi>That I ſhould oblige the King in going to the Nunnery of St.</hi> Maries <hi>of the</hi> Baſtile: And Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>De Touſſi</hi> came with ſix Guards to conduct me.</p>
            <p>Some time after Monſieur <hi>Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine</hi> going into <hi>Britany,</hi> came thither to ſee me; but was preſently out of all Patience, becauſe I wore Patches, (for I had ſome on by chance that day) and told me he would not ſpeak to me untill I had taken them off.</p>
            <p>No man ever made his Demands with ſuch unreaſonable haughtineſs, as deſerved rather to be refuſed than granted; and chiefly, when he believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that Conſcience was concerned; and that alſo was the reaſon I would not put off my Patches; to ſhew him it was neither of my Belief nor Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to offend God with this kind of Dreſſe.</p>
            <p>After Conteſting a whole hour about
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:45280:24"/>this in vain, he at laſt began to tell me his mind, notwithſtanding my pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; and preſſed me with as little ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to go with him into <hi>Brittany.</hi> I was then more inclinable to go to Law with him than to follow him. I obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed leave of his Majeſty to commence my Suit, having been Conducted to Him by the Princeſs of <hi>Baden.</hi> But Monſieur <hi>Colbert,</hi> who was very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to conſent to it, for Reaſons that admitted of no Anſwer, in any other Conjuncture: It put along de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay to it; until at laſt Madam <hi>De Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel</hi> being put into the ſame Monaſtery with me; I obtained, by the favour of ſome Friends that ſhe had at Court, leave to Commence my Suit.</p>
            <p>As ſhe was a very beautiful perſon, and of a very pleaſant humour, I had Complaiſance enough for her, to joyn with her in playing ſome Tricks to the Nunns.</p>
            <p>The King has been told a hundred ridiculous Stories about it: That we uſed to put Ink into the Holy-Water-Pot to ſmut the good old Nunns: That we uſed to run through their Dormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, at the time of their firſt Sleep,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:45280:24"/>with a great many little Doggs, yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and yellowing; and twenty other ſuch Fooleries, either altogether inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or much exaggarated. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, having deſired them to let us have ſome water to waſh our Feet, The Nuns concerted amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to refuſe us what was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and to find fault, as if we had been put in there to obſerve their Rule. It is true, that we filled two great Cheſts that where over the Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitory, with Water, and not taking notice, that the floor was ill ſoynted, the water run through, and wet all the poor Nunns beds. If you were at that time at Court, you will eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that this accident was repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented there as a meer Horſe-boyes pranke. It is alſo true, that under Colour of keeping us Company, they would never ſuffer us to go out of their Sights. The eldeſt amongſt the Religious women were choſen for this purpoſe, as being the hardeſt to be ſuborned; but we having nothing elſe to do but to run about, we ſoon tyred them out one after another, and one or two of them ſprained their
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:45280:25"/>Leggs, ſtriving to run after us. <hi>I</hi> ſhould not tell you theſe litle odd Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, if Monſieur <hi>Mazarins</hi> partiſans had not publiſhed them before; and ſince they repreſented them as ſo many Crimes, <hi>I</hi> am glad you know all the enormities of them. After we had been three months in this Covent, we had Leave to go to <hi>Chelles;</hi> where <hi>I</hi> knew we ſhould be more Civilly trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, though we could not have ſo many Viſits; and Monſieur <hi>Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine</hi> Arrived the ſame day from <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany,</hi> that we were removed thither. Some few days after, Monſieur <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarine</hi> Comes with a Guard of three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore Horſe, with pretention from Monſieur <hi>de Paris</hi> to enter the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery,</hi> and carry me away by force. But the <hi>Abbeſs</hi> not only refuſed him entrance, but put all the Keyes of the Houſe into my hands, to free me even from the ſuſpition of the evil ſhe might have done me. With this Condition only, that <hi>I</hi> would ſpeak to Monſieur <hi>Mazarine. I</hi> asked him what he would have? but he ſtill replied, <hi>I was not the</hi> Abbeſs. I anſwered him, <hi>I was the</hi> Abbeſs <hi>for him that Day, ſince all the Keyes of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:45280:25"/>the Houſe were in my Power, and there was no getting in for him but by my Favour.</hi> He turned his Back, and went his way. A Gentleman that Madam the Counteſs ſent, to know how <hi>I</hi> did, Carried this News to <hi>Paris,</hi> and ſayd, that it was repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Chelles,</hi> that Monſieur <hi>Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riue</hi> went off, onely with deſigne to returne againe in the Night. You have heard vvithout doubt how Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de Bovi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on,</hi> Monſieur the <hi>Count,</hi> Monſieur <hi>de Bovillon,</hi> and a number of the greateſt Perſons about the Court got on Horſe-back upon this Report, to come to my Reſque.</p>
            <p>At this Noiſe, they made, Madam <hi>Courcelles,</hi> and <hi>I</hi> took them for my Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; but our Fears vvas not ſo great but that vve thought upon an expedient to hide our ſelves; there vvas a hole in the Grate of our Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leour bigg enough for a great Diſh to paſs; and vve never till then thought one could Creep through it: Yet vve both got in at that Hole, but it vvas vvith ſo much difficulty, that if Monſieur <hi>Mazarin</hi> himſelf had been in that Parlour he vvould never ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:45280:26"/>that place, and would have looked for us any vvhere elſe, than there. But vvhen we found our Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, the ſhame and confuſion we vvere in, made us reſolve to ſhoot that Gulph once more vvithout Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling any body to our Ayd. Madam <hi>de Courcelle</hi> got eaſily through, but <hi>I</hi> was above a quarter of an hour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt two barrs of Iron, and almoſt ſqueeſed to Death vvithout being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to get in or out. But though <hi>I</hi> vvas horribly pinched, <hi>I</hi> would not conſent any ſhould be Called to help us; and Madam <hi>Courcel</hi> never left tugging until ſhe had me out. <hi>I</hi> went to thank them all, and after they had Joked a while upon Monſieur <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarines</hi> attempt to Catch nothing, they all returned back. In the mean time <hi>I</hi> had ſuch a Decree, as <hi>I</hi> deſired in in the third Court of Enqueſts: this Court conſiſted moſt of young men of great VVit and Eloquence, and they all ſtrove who ſhould be moſt forward to ſerve me. The ſcope of the Decretal Order was, <hi>That I ſhould be allowed twenty thouſand Livers a year. That I ſhould live at the Pallace
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:45280:26"/>Mazarine, and Monſieur Mazarine at the Arſenal.</hi> And what was more important? <hi>That Monſieur Mazarine ſhould be Obliged to produce the goods or their value, which I declared he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipated.</hi> Madam the Princeſs of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginan</hi> came to put me into poſſeſſion. There <hi>I</hi> found all the Servants that <hi>I</hi> had need of, already Choſen by Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Mazarine;</hi> but <hi>I</hi> thanked them all for their good will. Madam the Counteſs who always unſeaſonally put me in mind of my Generoſity, would fain perſwade me that it was below me to exact the allowance the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament had Aſſigned me. But Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> was not a man that would give me any thing without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Compell'd; and <hi>I</hi> muſt have whereby to ſubject. It is true, ſhe asked me if <hi>I</hi> had need of money; but ſhe could not be Ignorant of that; and were it not for my ſmall Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, and the helps <hi>I</hi> had from my Brother, my Affairs had been in a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ill poſture. He return'd out of <hi>Italy</hi> ten days after my Decree; and although he vvas very angry at my Law-ſute, for thoſe very Reaſons
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:45280:27"/>that made Monſ. <hi>Colvert</hi> to diſapprove of it, and that he always foretold me that madam the Counteſs vvould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake me as ſoon as ſhe had ingaged me in this buſineſs; yet I found every morning upon my Toylet more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney than <hi>I</hi> needed, without ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able truly to diſcover from vvhnce it came.</p>
            <p>In the intrim Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> remov'd the Suit unto the Great Chamber, for a new Trial; it vvas ſo order'd, that the King interpoſed in our affair to make a final accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation betwixt us. VVe both Signed a VVriting to the King to this effect, <hi>That Monſieur</hi> Mazarine <hi>ſhould return to Lodge at the Palace</hi> Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, <hi>but that I ſhould have the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to Choſe all my own Servants, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting my Gentleman of the Horſe, who was to be recommended to me by Monſieur</hi> Colbert; <hi>that we ſhould live each in their own Apartments, that I ſhould not be obliged to follow him in any of his Journeys: and as for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of Goods, I deſired the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of ſtate ſhould be Arbitrator, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and that we ſhould inviolably ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:45280:27"/>and obey their Award.</hi> Upon the ſame day that I ſigned this VVriting, I meeting Madam <hi>de Briſack</hi> at the Fair, who told me Laughing, Madam, you are plaſtred up again for the third time. Nor were we truly friends, for Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> made it his buſineſs to thwart me in all things, of vvhich I could inſtance many particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larities; but one ſhall ſerve that made noiſe enough; <hi>I</hi> had ordered a Stage to be Erected in my own appartment, to have a Comedy Acted for ſome Perſons of the Court. But Monſieur <hi>Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine</hi> cauſed it to be pulled down two houres before it vvas to be made uſe of, <hi>becauſe it was a Holy Day, and a Comedie was a prophane Divertiſement.</hi> But all this did not hinder, but that we ſaw one another very Civilly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very after Noon; for vve neither eat, nor lay together, though Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> would have it otherwiſe underſtood; but our award mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned nothing of it.</p>
            <p>Nor could I ſee any likely-hood, that our Affairs ſhould remain long in this poſture: and if happily our Affairs muſt be referred again to the Parliar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:45280:28"/>I was loath to expoſe my ſelf to the drudgery of Solliciting, being great with Child.</p>
            <p>Nor was my Apprehenſions vain; For, Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> was ſoon weary of what he had done; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon begged of His Majeſty to tear the Writings, and to Releaſe us of our Ingagements. Neither would I conſent to it, but upon condition that his Majeſty would never more inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe into our Buſineſs, neither one way nor other: His Majeſty was Graciouſly pleaſed to paſs His Word, that he would not, and has ever ſince kept His Promiſe. This brought us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into Parliament; and our Suit was followed with more Bitterneſs on both ſides than ever.</p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> and his Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents forgot nothing ſince that time, that might ſully my Reputation to the World; and a bove, all make me hateful to His Majeſty.</p>
            <p>The Extravagancies of Monſieur <hi>Courcelles,</hi> amongſt other things, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed them with an Admirable Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I had forgotten to tell you, that when I left <hi>Chelles,</hi> I prevailed ſo far,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:45280:28"/>that I got leave for his Wife to come a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> live with me She was no ſooner there, but thoſe that formerly had been inſtrumental to draw her away from her Husband, being glad to put her again into his Poſſeſſion, found means, I know not how, to let him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Pallace <hi>Mazarine,</hi> whilſt I was abroad; and managed her ſo, that her Husband and ſhe went away together as good friends as ever. One day as I came to giver her a Viſit, ſhe was ſo fooliſh as to deny her ſelf, though Mr. <hi>Cavoy</hi>'s Coach ſtood at the Door. In the firſt tranſports of my Paſſion, for this her Rudeneſs, her Husband came unluckily in the way, to whom I could not forbear ſaying ſomething of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>This fooliſh Fellow of late hankered after an occaſion to fight <hi>Cavoy;</hi> and was loath it ſhould be thought that he was Jealous of the beſt of his Friends, but that it was upon ſome other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. The moſt Plauſible he could find, was, to pretend himſelf every where in in love with me; giving out, <hi>That his Wife had in her keeping ſome Letters of mine that were of Conſequence, and which I had written to ſome Gentleman
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:45280:29"/>of the Court; That ſhe put them into</hi> Cavoye's <hi>hands; and that</hi> Cavoy, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Raſcal, ſhewed them about; but that he would force him with his Sword to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtore them, as he had promiſed meſo to do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although this Story was Ridiculous enough, and as ill contrived as might be, yet it found Belief; and ſome were ſo ſooliſh as to report it for a Truth.</p>
            <p>He did worſe than all this; he had the Impudence to tell me to my Face of it, in the Court-Yard of the Pallace <hi>Mazarine. I told him, that knowing better than any other, that all he had ſaid was not true; I could not imagine he could have any other Deſign in it, but to make himſelf merry:</hi> and that, <hi>if I knew that he had the leaſt intention of Fighting upon this Ridiculous Pretence, I would immediately acquaint Monſieur the</hi> Count <hi>with it, who was juſt by, and heard ſome part of our Diſcourſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Courſel</hi> perceiving, by the manner and tone of my Voice, that I would not underſtand Rallery, made ſigne with a nod of his head, that it was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in jeſt; not daring to ſpeak it out,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:45280:29"/>becauſe of Monſieur the Count, who joyned us at the ſame time.</p>
            <p>It is eaſie to gueſs how great my a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement was, when I underſtood the next day that they had not only fought, but that likewiſe in the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord they made amongſt themſelves in the Field, He had the Impudence to maintain this Fiction to the end; and to except a Woman from the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret they had mutually promiſed to keep. He was ſo well pleaſed with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that he could not contain himſelf, but Braggs of this Exception to all people without Exception; which made the matter publick, and was the occaſion that they both were ſent to the <hi>Conciergery,</hi> to do Penance for one man's Folly. They were not wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at Court in their Cenſures of me, upon this occaſion, treating me with the Attributes of Incendary, make-bate and Brutal; That I ſhould be the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of cutting many other Throats, if I could.</p>
            <p>One of my Grooms of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber being dangerouſly wounded about that time by ſome of his drunken Comrades, they had the Charity to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:45280:30"/>inform the King, <hi>That this Fellow was privy to all my Secrets, and that having found that he betrayed his Truſt,</hi> I took courſe to have him aſſaſſinated. The inſolent Liberty people took to charge me with theſe Calumnies, obliged me to ſpeak to the King about it. <hi>Madam</hi> the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> in whoſe Company I went to him, told him as ſhe entred the Room, <hi>That ſhe brought him that Criminal, that wicked Woman, of whom ſo many evil things had been told him.</hi> The King was pleaſed to tell me, <hi>That he never gave Credit to any of thoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports:</hi> But his manner of delivering this, was ſo ſuccinct, and ſo far from the accuſtomed Civility with which he uſed to hear me, that all others but my ſelf, would have doubted of the Truth of what he ſaid; you know the Court is a land of much contradiction. The Compaſſion which perhaps peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple took of me, when they ſaw me ſhut up in a Convent, was changed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Envy, to ſee me appear in the Queens with-drawing Room, and to make a much better appearance there than I had a mind to. Yet I had no other pretention, but to endeavour to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:45280:30"/>make ſome tollerable Agreement with Monſieur <hi>Mazarine;</hi> but thoſe by whoſe Counſels I regulated my Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Affairs, having other ends, ruined my buſineſs, by endeavouring to make their own ſucceed; &amp; ſo abuſing my ſimplicity, and the blind Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence <hi>I</hi> gave to all their Advices, made me run up and down to this place, and that man, without under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the reaſon or conſequence of it.</p>
            <p>Admidſt all theſe Troubles and Vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations, our Suit went forward, and Mounſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> found the ſame favour amongſt the Old men, which <hi>I</hi> had obtained of the Young. After three months time, <hi>I</hi> had Intelligence, <hi>That he had gained the Hearts of the great Chamber, that his Cabal carried all before them there, that he was like to have ſuch a Decree as he deſired; that although they did grant me the ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Goods, they would not leave me that of my Bed, which I then enjoyed, and therefore was no part of my Requeſt to them; and laſtly, that the Judges could not diſpence with themſelves from ordering me to go to</hi> Cohabit <hi>with my
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:45280:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>Husband, though they had been as fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable as they were then avers to me.</hi> If this account had been given me by people of leſs credit then they from whom <hi>I</hi> had it, <hi>I</hi> might have had the liberty of publiſhing the Names of my Authors. But as they run a ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard in telling it, ſo they were cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious in exacting my Secrecy, which <hi>I</hi> will eternally keep inviolable to them. You may judge what uſage <hi>I</hi> was like to have of Monſieur <hi>Mazarine,</hi> if <hi>I</hi> ſhould be forced by Act of Parliament to return to him, after the cauſes of Reſentments which he pretended to have againſt me, and have both Court and Parliament, contrary to me.</p>
            <p>Theſe were the Motives that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced that ſtrange and ſo much blam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Reſolution, which <hi>I</hi> took, of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiring into <hi>Italy,</hi> to my Friends and Relations, ſeeing now no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Refuge or Security for me in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Brother, who was at once, the neareſt, the deareſt, and the diſcreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of my Relations, was alſo of the firſt that approved of my Reſolution,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:45280:31"/>and offered me all he could doe to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour it. The Chevalier of <hi>Rohan,</hi> his intimate Friend, and mine, having, <hi>I</hi> know not how heard of it, ſpoke to us ſo knowingly of it, that we could not without Impudence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal it from him, nor without ſome kind of Ingratitude refuſe his aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
            <p>My Deſigne was not to go directly then to <hi>Rome,</hi> but only to <hi>Millan,</hi> to ſee my Siſter the Conſtable of <hi>Col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nna,</hi> whither <hi>I</hi> writ to her to come, and ſtay for me, that ſhe might bear me Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany to <hi>Bruxelles;</hi> that from thence, as being nearer, we might with more eaſe, negotiate ſome more durable and advantagious Agreement with Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> than the former had proved.</p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>De Rohan</hi> begged that he might come to us thither along with my Brother, when we ſhould be arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved there; nor could we in Civility refuſe it him. <hi>I</hi> had ſome reaſons to believe, that Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> would be more eaſily wrought to a better accomodation, when he ſhould once ſee me out of <hi>France.</hi> And the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:45280:32"/>Apprehenſions <hi>I</hi> marked in him every time <hi>I</hi> threatned to be gone, would not ſuffer me to doubt of it.</p>
            <p>The Deſpaire to which he did often reduce me, made me many times tell him, <hi>That if I were once out of of his reach, I would make him run far enough, before he ſhould over-take me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to my misfortune, he never belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved I had ſo much courage, untill he ſaw it. After I had taken this Reſolution, <hi>I</hi> ſo much neglected my ſuit, that I have a hundred times ſince wondred, that thoſe, who were concerned in it, did not perceive it. Madam the Counteſs, of whom I was moſt affraid was the only perſon that had ſome ſuſpicion of it, but ſhe gave it no Credit: She came almoſt every day to my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, where ſhe found us always very merry in appearance, to deceive the World; ſhe cried out upon me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I did not ſolicit my buſineſs, that it was a great ſhame for me to let my ſuit be loſt for want of looking after it. Some eight days before I parted, She was there when one of my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:45280:32"/>Gentlemen, called <hi>Parnullac,</hi> came to take his leave of us, <hi>He pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to go to ſee his Father, who (as he ſaid) had ſome command in</hi> Lorraine <hi>among the Horſe.</hi> But in Truth, it was to order Poſt Horſes to be ready for me upon that Road, which I choſe becauſe it was the unlikelieſt to be ſuſpected. The ſight of this man that was to begin my enterpriſe, put me into ſuch diſorder, that I have ſince wondered how the Counteſs did not take notice of it; ſhe was taken up with gloſſing upon my Negligence in the midſt of ſo many important Concerns. <hi>That it was not the time to ſtay all day in my Chamber undreſſed, playing upon my Guittare, and that this kind of Careleſneſs made her al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt believe what was reported, that I intended to fly into</hi> Italy. Theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable Remonſtrances ended in an Exhortation to me, to go with her to St. <hi>Germaine</hi> to make my Court at leaſt. But I pray'd her excuſe; having other buſineſs that concerned me nearer. It was abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for my concerns that ſhe ſhould be at St. <hi>Germaine</hi> when I parted; for
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:45280:33"/>if ſhe were at <hi>Paris;</hi> in the diſtruſt ſhe had had of my Conduct, it had been almoſt impoſſible, but ſhe would have ſuſpected ſomthing of my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</p>
            <p>In fine, <hi>VVedneſday</hi> the thirteenth of <hi>June</hi> in the year one thouſand ſix Hundred and ſixty eight, being the day appointed for my Departure, whil'ſt I was putting my litle Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs in order againſt Night, ſhe ſent for me to go dine with her at Saint <hi>Germaine;</hi> I was about to ſend her word I could not go, but the meſſenger was ordered to take no denial, but that I muſt go; which made me ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend my Plot was diſcovered; but as we muſt allways in ſuch kind of matters preſume we are not diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, though we ſee never ſo great appearances to the Contrary, I thought it expedient to Promiſe, I would meet her there leſt ſhe ſhould come her ſelf to fetch me.</p>
            <p>When dinner time was over, and <hi>I</hi> did not appear, ſhe ſent to conjure me not to fail to come thither before Night. <hi>I</hi> excuſed my ſelf as well as <hi>I</hi> could for breaking my Word, and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:45280:33"/>bid them aſſure her that <hi>I</hi> would not fail to be there at Night; but ten of the Clock being paſſed, and no News of me, ſhe took her Coach and came ſtreight towards <hi>Parts.</hi> She was come above half way when ſhe met my Brother, who leſt <hi>Paris</hi> at the ſame time I did, to impart my Deſign to Monſieur <hi>De Louvoy.</hi> She asked him abruptly, <hi>Where I was?</hi> But he ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her, <hi>If ſhe had not met me?</hi> ſhe ſaid <hi>No:</hi> He replyed coldly, <hi>That ſure then I had taken the other Road; for, that he ſaw me come away before he took Coach.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> came to awake the King at three of the Clock in the morning, to beſeech him that he would give order, That I ſhould be purſued. But His Majeſty had the Generoſity to anſwer him: <hi>That he would not break the Promiſe he had made when he tore our Award, never to meddle with any of our Concerns, one way nor another; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was it likely to over-take me now, being ſo long gone; and having taken my Meaſures at leaſure as I had done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this Anſwer was otherwiſe ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to the world; and you have ſurely
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:45280:34"/>heard of the Verſes which were made of this Subject, which begins thus:
<q>Sad <hi>Mazarine,</hi> pale and full of grief.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And ended with this Joke upon the Revelations he had, during the Queens great ſickneſs, touching the King and Madam <hi>La Valiers.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Alaſs, what is become of my poor Wife?</l>
               <l>Know you not (quoth the King?) ſure you cannot miſs.</l>
               <l>Th'Angel that tells you all has told you this.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>Mazarine,</hi> ſeeing he could obtain nothing to his purpoſe of the King, went to Monſieur <hi>Colbert,</hi> who adviſed him to ſend ſome Perſon of Credit after me, to offer me my own Terms ſo I would come back. It was one Monſieur <hi>Louvier,</hi> one of the Lieutenants of the Ordinance who was ſent; and you may judge from the place where he over-took me, that the King had reaſon to ſay, It was then too late to follow me.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:45280:34"/>
            <p>Whilſt things paſſed thus at Court, I ran a ſtrange Carreir: and I do aſſure you, that if I had fore-ſeen all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies that attends ſuch a Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, I ſhould rather have choſen to end my dayes betwixt four Walls, or make my ſelf away with Steel or Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, than to expoſe my Reputation, to thoſe Calumnies that are inevitable to all Women of my Age and Quality, that are ſeparated from their Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands.</p>
            <p>Though I had not Experience e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, nor thoſe that were of my Counſel, fore-caſt enough; yet I was not without many Conflicts with my ſelf before I could abſolutely come to a ſetled Determination: And my Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions were ſo trobleſom to me, that if you could but ſee them, you would more eaſily comprehend that nothing but the neceſſity I ſaw my ſelf reduced to, could hurry me to ſo pernicious an Enterpriſe.</p>
            <p>I can with great Truth aſſure you, that all my Divertiſments were but feigned ſince I had formed this deſigne; and that Madam the Counteſs was much in the wrong in reproaching me with
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:45280:35"/>my tranquility of mind; <hi>I</hi> ſcarce took any reſt, nor eat, nor drank much for above eight days before; and <hi>I</hi> was ſo much troubled when <hi>I</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that <hi>I</hi> was fain to ſend back from the Gate of St. <hi>Anthony,</hi> to fetch the Box in which was my money and my Jewels which <hi>I</hi> had forgotten. It is a great Truth that I never dreamed that <hi>I</hi> ſhould ever want money, but experience hath taught me it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the firſt thing, that is wanting, eſpecially to thoſe, that having always lived in great plenty of it, never know the neceſſity and importance of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly managing it.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, I left the Keys of my Appartment with my Brother, that he might ſeize upon my Plate, Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture and other things of Value. But he was ſo Careleſs as to let Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> prevent him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame token that ſomtime af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward he ſould ſome of my things to Madam <hi>La Valter</hi> for a hundred thouſand Francks. My Train Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted of a maid <hi>I</hi> had but ſix months, called <hi>Nannon,</hi> dreſſed immans Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel, as <hi>I</hi> was, a man of my Brothers
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:45280:35"/>called <hi>Narciſſus,</hi> with whom <hi>I</hi> had no acquaintance, and a Gentleman be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Monſieur <hi>Rohan</hi> called <hi>Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bevil,</hi> whom <hi>I</hi> had never ſeen before. My Brother prayed Monſieur <hi>Rohan</hi> not to leave me until he had ſeen me out of Town, <hi>I</hi> parted with him without the Gate of St. <hi>Anthony,</hi> and drove on in a Goach with ſix Horſes, to a houſe belonging to the Princeſs of <hi>Guimene</hi> his mother, ten Leagues from <hi>Paris.</hi> From thence I went ſix or ſeven Leagues in a <hi>Caleche;</hi> but theſe kind of Carriages were too ſlow for my Fears, therefore <hi>I</hi> took Horſe, and Arrived at <hi>Bar,</hi> the Friday following about Noon; from thence (ſeeing my ſelf out of <hi>France</hi>) <hi>I</hi> went no further than <hi>Nancy</hi> that Night. The Duke of <hi>Lorraine</hi> hearing of my Arrival, and deſireing to ſee me, was ſo Civil as not to preſs it, when he underſtood <hi>I</hi> was unwilling. The Reſident of <hi>France</hi> was very earneſt to have me ſtopped there, but in vain; and the Duke, to Compleat his Generoſity, gave me a Lieutenant and twenty of his Guards to Conduct me into <hi>Swiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerland.</hi> VVe were almoſt every where known to be VVomen; and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:45280:36"/>
               <hi>Nanon</hi> ſtill through forgetfulneſs cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led me Madam; whether for this Reaſon, or that my Face gave ſome Cauſe of ſuſpition; the People wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched us through the Keyhole, when we had ſhut our ſelves in, and ſaw our long Treſſes, which as ſoon as we were at liberty we untied, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were very troubleſome to us under our Perriwigs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nanon</hi> was extreme low of ſtature, and ſo unfit to be Cloathed in mens Apparel, that I could never look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her without Laughing. The Night that I lay at <hi>Nancy,</hi> where we reaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed our Womens Apparel, <hi>I</hi> was ſo overjoyed to ſee my ſelf out of danger, that <hi>I</hi> gave my ſelf the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of diverting me a litle at my or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Sports, and as I ran after her to Laugh at her, I fell on my Knee ſo that <hi>I</hi> hurt it, but <hi>I</hi> did not feel it then; ſome dayes after <hi>I</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a Bed to be made in a pittiful Village of the <hi>French</hi> County, to reſt my ſelf while Dinner was a prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, but of a ſuddain ſuch a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous paine took me in that Knee, that <hi>I</hi> was not able to riſe; but on
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:45280:36"/>
               <hi>I</hi> muſt go, therefore having been let blood by a woman for want of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chirurgion, <hi>I</hi> followed my Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in a Litter till <hi>I</hi> came to <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle,</hi> where the people perſwaded themſelves, that I was Madam <hi>de Longe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville;</hi> you cannot Imagine the Joy, the people expreſſed to ſee me, being not uſed to ſee Women of Quality of <hi>France,</hi> paſſe through their Country; nor could they comprehend that any other then the Dutcheſs of <hi>Longe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville</hi> could have buſineſs that way. <hi>I</hi> know ſome would have layd hold of this occaſion, and made uſe of their kindneſs, to taſt of the ſweetneſs of Soveraignity, however the miſtake was advantagious to me; and what <hi>I</hi> wanted in Age, <hi>I</hi> gained in qualli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. But this Authority ſeemed to me too great and too good for a Fugitive; <hi>I</hi> was alſo ſo unskilfully handled, that my paine grew worſe, in ſo much that <hi>I</hi> had once thoughts of returning to <hi>Paris;</hi> and were it not that <hi>Millain</hi> was nearer, and that <hi>I</hi> hoped to be ſooner and ſafer there, <hi>I</hi> had purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my firſt Thoughts.</p>
            <p>Some few days after, as <hi>I</hi> paſſed
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:45280:37"/>through a litle Town of <hi>Swiſzerland,</hi> where we were all like to be knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Head, by our Ignorance of their Language: and to compleat our happineſs, we underſtood when we came to <hi>Altauph,</hi> that we muſt paſs our Quarantaine there, before we ſhould be ſuffred to enter the Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of <hi>Millan.</hi> There it was my ſtock of Patience was quite ſpent For <hi>I</hi> faw my ſelf in a Barbarous Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, moſt deſperately Sick, full of grievous Pain; and for Help, you ſhall Judg by what hapned to <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſſus,</hi> whether there was much to be hoped for in that place. For he ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſomthing, ſent for a Chirurgion to let him Blood, they brought him a <hi>Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier,</hi> who going to let him Blood with his Flemmes miſſed the Vain, and <hi>Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſſus</hi> threatning to kill him, the Fellow ſtill anſwered Coldly, <hi>that he had not hurt the Artery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what conſummated and through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly carried my Condition, even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Deſpair, was the Diviſion that I found in my Family, and their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Jarring. <hi>Narciſſus</hi> took it Ill, that <hi>Courbevill</hi> who had been in my
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:45280:37"/>Family but ſeven or eight dayes, ſhould take upon him to meddle with any thing without his leave; and the ſame reaſon made <hi>Nanon</hi> quarrel with them both; but while <hi>Narciſſus</hi> and ſhe Jarred in this manner, they were wholly uſeleſs to me, and did nothing but out of ſpite to thwart one another.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide <hi>Courbevill</hi> was very diligent to help me; and I am ſtill perſwaded, had it not been for him, I had been forced to had my Legg cut off. And as my diſtreſſed Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition made me very thankful, and acknowledging for every little ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; and commending his particular Care of me, put them two quite out of Humour; and thereupon aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd me wholly to his Care of me.</p>
            <p>It was at the time of this Quaran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, that <hi>La Louvier</hi> over-took me; but <hi>I</hi> remitted his Deliberation of what he propoſed to me, to our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival at <hi>Millan,</hi> whither <hi>I</hi> came ſome few dayes after, by the favour and means of the Duke of <hi>Seſt,</hi> Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Law to the Conſtable, and Governour of that Country: He un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:45280:38"/>how I was detained at <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauph,</hi> and he remitted eighteen dayes of my Quarantine. My Siſter and the Conſtable came to meet me at a Houſe of theirs four dayes Journey from <hi>Millan,</hi> where we ſtayed ſome dayes, and thence we went to <hi>Millan,</hi> where in ſix weeks that we ſtaied there, we received nine Couriers from <hi>Parris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> underſtood that preſently after my flight, the Judges had declared themſelves in my favour againſt Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Mazarine;</hi> and that the Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>I</hi> had taken, gave at the ſame time both Admiration and Pitty to all reaſonable people; and that Monſieur <hi>Turren</hi> himſelf had ſpoken to the King in my behalf. But things quickly changed of face by my friends joyning with Monſieur <hi>Mazarine,</hi> in an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal againſt my Brother and Monſieur <hi>Rohan,</hi> who alledged in his Bill, that they had ſtole me away.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> know that Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> ſent one after me with power to take Information, from place to place, all the Road that <hi>I</hi> paſſed, of all my A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Demeanure.</p>
            <p>And this perhaps is the greateſt and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:45280:38"/>only Obligation <hi>I</hi> owe him, ſince this mans Depoſitions which are Recorded in Parliament, are undeniable Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Innocence of my car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage and conduct throughout this Journey, againſt all the Allegations and Aſperſions of my Enemies. But this was not the beſt Story in his Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get: <hi>I</hi> had written to my Brother, and to Monſieur <hi>Rohan</hi> before <hi>I</hi> left <hi>New Caſtel;</hi> to my Brother to let him know where, and how <hi>I</hi> was; and to Monſieur <hi>Rohan,</hi> to thank him for the Service he did me at my coming away, in facilitating my Departure. <hi>I</hi> had commanded <hi>Narciſſus</hi> to ſend away theſe Letters by the Poſt, but whether it was that his hatred to <hi>Courbevill</hi> reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as far as his Maſters that gave him me, or that it was meer negligence, he confeſſed at <hi>Millan</hi> that he forgot Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Rohan</hi>'s Letter upon the Mantle-Tree in the Poſt-maſter's Houſe at <hi>New-Caſtle,</hi> to whom he had given it incharge. <hi>La Louvier</hi> finding it as he came that way, carried it with him, and gave it to Monſieur <hi>Mazarine,</hi> who made wonderful uſe of it, and with ſuch ſucceſs, that it ſet all the World
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:45280:39"/>againſt me: And it was upon this Letter that he grounded his Requeſt, ſometimes after, that I ought to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit all my Rights, which is never pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed but againſt Women, convinced of the higheſt Infamy and Lewedneſs.</p>
            <p>I told you that Monſieur <hi>Rohan</hi> had obtained my Brothers conſent to come to us to <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> when we ſhould be arrived there. The Need we had of him, having made us conclude the matter ſo; it was natural enough to mention this to him, in a Letter that was deſigned principally to ſhew him my Acknowledgements and Gratitude. This was Evidence enough for Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> to prove a Confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy betwixt us, and that the Chevalier was in love with me. But beſides, that his Affections were known to the whole Court to be ingaged elſe-where then, and to a Perſon of that Eminent Quality, that he was Baniſhed for it: His manner of proceeding did no way ſhew any ſuch thing. It was truly the part of a good Friend to furniſh me with means to convey my ſelf far off, and to put me into the hands of truſty Servants; But it was no way
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:45280:39"/>that of a true Lover; there are very few that being favoured with a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of this Nature, would be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to loſe ſight of their Miſtriſs in ſo Extraordinary an Occaſion as this.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding all this, the world gave Credit to what Monſieur <hi>Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine</hi> would have paſs for a Truth: As for my Brother, he had, as you have ſeen by the Story, took up a Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of him, to render him ſuſpected in all my Concerns; that by this means he might deprive me of ſo conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Support: there is nothing ſo inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, but is poiſoned, to maintain &amp; car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on ſo deteſtable a Calumny; they produced Letters in verſe, for want of other Evidences</p>
            <p>Poſterity (if happily any thing of our Buſineſs does reach it) will hardly believe that a man of my Brothers Gravity ſhould be examined upon In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogatories about ſuch Trifles; and that they ſhould be ſeriouſly diſcuſſed before ſo grave a Bench: That they ſhould make ſuch a Deteſtable uſe of ſo innocent a Commerce of Wit and Fancy, betwixt perſons ſo nearly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated: To conclude, That the Eſteem and Friendſhip I had for a Brother,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:45280:40"/>of a Deſert and Merit ſo well known, and ſo juſtly due to him, and who loved me intirely well, ſhould be made uſe of as an injuſt Pretence and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour for ſo Black and ſo Cruel a Defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
            <p>It will be hard to find ſtranger Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of the Misfortunes of a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of my Quality, Sex, and Age.</p>
            <p>The moſt ſacred Tyes of Nature and Reaſon, become the moſt horrible Crimes when Jealouſie and Envy comes to deſcant upon them: and there is nothing impoſſible to a man that makes Profeſſion of Piety and Devotion, rather than he ſhall be thought in the wrong; the moſt Innocent and Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Perſons in the World, ſhall be thought the moſt Infamous, and the moſt Abominable. I may perhaps be thought in Paſſion; but the Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of ſo Barbarous a Wrong, and ſo Cruel Uſage, has run me into a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous Digreſſion. For, it is very difficult to keep an even Temper in Relating ſuch Sad and Lamentable Things.</p>
            <p>Nor is it eaſie to leave wondring that People ſhould be ſo malicious as
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:45280:40"/>to tax me with a Buſineſs ſo known to the World as the Friendſhip and Union that was betwixt my Siſter the Conſtable, my Brother, and my Self.</p>
            <p>The whole Court of <hi>France</hi> have ſeen a Letter, which he writ from <hi>Rome</hi> ſometime after our Marriages, wherein he repreſents to one of his Friends, his Happineſs in having two Siſters whom he loved ſo well, living in two of the Greateſt and moſt Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Cityes of the World, <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Paris.</hi> He ended his Letter with theſe two Verſes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>And thus I paſs my dayes in great Delight,</l>
               <l>With Wiſe <hi>Mary,</hi> and <hi>Hartenſia</hi> Bright.</l>
            </q>
            <p>It is not unluckily, but that Monſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eur <hi>Mazarine</hi> would have made uſe of theſe Verſes, in his Suit, if my Siſter (whom he endeavoured to gain, and ſet againſt me) had not been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in them as well as I: For, they are, at leaſt, as Criminal and Faulty as the other Letter, of which he made
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:45280:41"/>uſe. My Brother writ me that other Letter to St. <hi>Germain,</hi> where I was ſome dayes, after Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> had cauſed the Stage to be thrown down, which I told you I had ordered to be ſet up in my Appartment. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun thus:
<q>
                  <l>Thou art in thy kind without Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare,</l>
                  <l>Chaſter than <hi>Lucrece,</hi> than <hi>Venus</hi> more Fair.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>He continues it with returning me thanks for writing to him, and giving me an account of his Health; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he goes on thus:</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Know then your kind Duke makes a damnable Rout,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He frets, and he fumes, and he wanders about,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And all to enquire his Dear</hi> Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine <hi>out.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He came th'other Night in a</hi> Lunatick <hi>Rage,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And told me the Tragical Fate of your Stage.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:45280:41"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Duke of</hi> Navaille, <hi>that withered ſad Drivel,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whoſe Gaſhly wild Looks would half fright the Devil,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To aſſiſt your Good-man comes Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d'ring Pell-mell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And with Noyſe, and with Non-ſenſe upon me he fell.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They both joyn'd i'th'</hi> Chorus, <hi>and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening their Throats.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ud as they could, with their damn'd Screetch-Owle Notes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They try'd me and teiz'd for a whole Hour long;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And his dear</hi> Mazarine <hi>was the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den o'th' Song.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your Hectoring Spouſe, like a Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen, ſtares,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Looks big, and all that, — and by's Maker he Swears,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He'l ſeize you by Force, when e'r he meets you.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And when in his Clutches but once more he gets you,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For all your Brisk Champions he'l care not a Rope;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He'l keep you in Spight of King, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, or Pope.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:45280:42"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>His Servant</hi> Polaſtron <hi>has offer'd his Aid,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To joyne in the Plot, to have you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Has Sworne his Allegiance the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to warrant</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Himſelf a true Squire to your new-made Knight Errant.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In this extream Danger, till the Tempeſt is o're,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Protection of</hi> Lewis, <hi>I adviſe you implore.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In all this Diſtreſs of his Friendſhip make tryal;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſhielded by his great Authority Royal,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You need fear no Ill. You'l be ſafely ſecur'd</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Againſt an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngrateful and Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Lord.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>The reſt is nothing. As I was ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Letter to ſome of my Friends at Court, the Count of <hi>Grammon</hi> came and ſnatched it out of my hands and carryed it to the King; it was read publickly before Him, and there was none of all the Court that was any way ſcandalized at it, but one of the King's
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:45280:42"/>Chyrurgions, named <hi>Eliam:</hi> This man, who in Appearance was zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for his Patients, hearing theſe Words,
<q>The Duke of <hi>Novaille,</hi> that wither'd ſad Drivel,</q> could not contain himſelf from inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting them, and ſaying. <hi>That was nothing; for he was ſhortly to be Purged.</hi> And yet it was upon ſuch Convincing Proofs as theſe, That Monſ. <hi>Mazarine</hi> obtained an Order of Parliament, to Arreſt me in any place where he ſhould find me.</p>
            <p>All my Friends, at the ſame time, Signed a Paper to him, joyntly pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Monſieur the <hi>Conſtable</hi> not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive me into his Houſe; but he laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at their Folly. And they had likewiſe ſent with them theſe other ſcandulous Letters. There came to me at the ſame time a particular Courier from the Counteſſe, to excuſe her ſelf to me about this; but by word of mouth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <p>I confeſs my Conſtancy was not of ſtrength enough to receive ſo great a
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:45280:43"/>Shock of ſo many Afflictions together. I fell into a deep Melancholly, and theſe kind of proceedings leaving me no hope of an Accomodation, <hi>I</hi> left off the Thoughts of going to <hi>Bruxelles.</hi> Hereupon my Brother arrives; and inſtead of Comforting me, he began a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Perſecution againſt me, ſo much the more Cruel, becauſe it had ſuch a Specious Foundation.</p>
            <p>It was agreed, that <hi>Courbevil</hi> ſhould be ſent back as ſoon as <hi>I</hi> came to <hi>Millain.</hi> But he having underſtood the Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Proceſs that was begun at <hi>Paris,</hi> in which he was made a party; he threw himſelf at my Feet, and repreſented to me, <hi>That he could not return to his Maſter, without carrying his Head to a Scaffold; and that having not whereby to ſubſiſt any where elſe, he ſhould be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ruined if I diſcharged him my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</hi> This Gentleman had been ſo ſerviceable to me in my greateſt Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, that <hi>I</hi> believed <hi>I</hi> could not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon him without extream Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude; therefore <hi>I</hi> paſſed my word to him that <hi>I</hi> would not put him away, as long as he would pleaſe to ſtay with me. And the cruel Diſpleaſures which
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:45280:43"/>
               <hi>I</hi> received for having kept him, have not yet perſwaded me that <hi>I</hi> ought not to have given him my word to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue him in my Service.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Narciſſus</hi> and <hi>Nanon</hi> enraged be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>I</hi> kept him, told my Brother that he talked inſolently of him; what they alledged he had ſaid was likely enough; my Brother believed them, and would have me turn him away: But as I knew who it was that had done him this ill Office, I could neither believe it, nor diſcharge him. But my Reſolution to keep him drove <hi>Narciſſus</hi> and <hi>Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on</hi> into deſpair; at laſt the beſt Expedient they could find to force me to ſatisfie their deſire, was to give out that <hi>Courbevil</hi> was in love with me.</p>
            <p>My Brother, who would ſeem igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of theſe ſervices, and of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe <hi>I</hi> gave him, and the Obligations <hi>I</hi> owed to this man, becauſe he believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf affronted by him, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accuſtomed to receive no Denyal from me, was afraid there was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing extraordinary in my Obſtinacy not to diſmiſs him: and was confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this Opinion, when after highly
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:45280:44"/>repreſenting to me the Report that was ſpread abroad, he ſaw I would not yield to part with him. This ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous Calumny inſtead of convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, did rather exaſperate me: And I was ſo neerly touched to find he gave Credit to it, that I could no longer endure him. The Conſtable and my Siſter were firſt of my ſide, againſt him; but they too turned to his ſide at laſt. Then there was nothing but fending and proving betwixt us four, and I was ſtill in the fault; and they juſtified themſelves at my Coſt.</p>
            <p>This kind of Life, full of Vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Reſentments, againſt a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and a Siſter whom I loved ſo dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and whoſe Society alone I thought ſufficient to make me happy, made me at laſt, though late, to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend that we muſt ſet our Hearts upon nothing in this World.</p>
            <p>In the midſt of theſe Diſquiets we came to <hi>Venis,</hi> where the Conſtable was not well at his eaſe, becauſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps he ſaw my Siſter was too well pleaſed to be there. He promiſed me great matters to induce me to go to <hi>Rome; That he would ingage his Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:45280:44"/>ſhould protect me;</hi> and <hi>that he would omit nothing to divert me from the deep Melancholly he ſaw me inclined to.</hi> Seeing my ſelf ſo cruelly perſecuted by my Brother, I thought it convenient, by my Complaiſance, to manage the Conſtable's Kindneſs. We went all to <hi>Sienne,</hi> to Cardinal <hi>Chigies;</hi> from whence, after three Weeks ſtay there, my Brother having fallen out with us, returned to <hi>Venis</hi> without taking leave of us, and we ſteered our courſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Rome;</hi> where the heats were ſo Exceſſive, that we were forced to retire for ſix weeks to <hi>Marine,</hi> a houſe of Pleaſure, belonging to my Brother-in-Law, the Conſtable.</p>
            <p>About the time we returned to <hi>Rome,</hi> my Brother came thither with a Gentleman belonging to <hi>Monſieur de Rohan,</hi> to cauſe (as I have been told) <hi>Courbevil</hi> to be Aſſaſſinated. I have been informed that <hi>Courbevil</hi> finding himſelf extream ill at <hi>Ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſe,</hi> he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved himſelf Poyſoned; and in this Belief he writ terrible Letters to <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> againſt my Brother: and Monſieur <hi>De Rohan,</hi> whom he believed of Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence with my Brother to have him
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:45280:45"/>turned him out of my Service; that theſe Letters falling into Monſieur <hi>De Rohan</hi>'s hands, he ſent them back to my Brother, deſiring him to Chaſtiſe <hi>Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bivil</hi> according to his Deſerts. The indiſcretion of this <hi>Courbevil,</hi> and the unpleaſing Noiſe this Buſineſs made in the World, together with the deſire I had to be at quiet, made me reſolve at laſt to diſcharge <hi>Courbevil;</hi> not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but he would willingly acquit me of my Promiſe which I had given him.</p>
            <p>My Requeſt to the the Preſident of <hi>Champlaſtreux</hi> his Son, who did nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate betwixt my Brother and me, was, <hi>That he ſhould not preſſe me with ſo much Imperiouſneſs to this Deferrence; and that I might be allowed to go and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journe with my Aunt</hi> Martinozzi. An Hour before <hi>Courbevil</hi> was to leave my Houſe, my Aunt being already come to carry me with her, my Siſter was in ſuch a rage becauſe I would no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſtay at her houſe, that ſhe begun to play upon him before me, and to ask him, If he would not once more move me, and perſwade me to let him ſtay yet this time? The man being in
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:45280:45"/>deſpair for his going away, anſwered her fiercely, <hi>That if I did not command him to go he would not, and that he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for none there but me.</hi> She bad <hi>him to get him gone, and that he ſhould un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what it was to ſpeak to her in her own Pallace with ſo little Reſpect.</hi> He went out in a great Fury, and I had reaſon to believe that there was ſome miſchief intended againſt him; and therefore thinking my ſelf bound to ſave his Life, I had him along with me to my Uncles Houſe, the Cardinal <hi>Mancini,</hi> from thence I went to my Aunt's Houſe, where I ſtaid ſome time ſhut cloſe up as in a Priſon.</p>
            <p>As Melancholy as I was, I could not hold Laughing at a requeſt ſhe made me, to dance the <hi>Mattaſſin Dance,</hi> to the Sound of my <hi>Guitar</hi> to divert me from Sadneſs, I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was this my Refuſe that did exaſperate her againſt me; but one day as I was at the Window, ſhe commanded me very roughly to get me from thence, <hi>That it was not the cuſtome at Rome to ſtand looking out at VVindows.</hi> Another time as I ſtood at it, ſhe ſent me her Ghoſtly Father to tell
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:45280:46"/>me <hi>That ſhe would cauſe me to be haled from it be force.</hi> This Monk was ſo inſolent in the delivery of his meſſage, that the Tears guſhed out of my Eyes. Cardinal <hi>Chigeis</hi> Gentleman of the Horſe, who was managing of Horſes before the Houſe, hearing me complain, came up to offer me his Service, but when I ſaw him, I had no power of ſaying any more. For all that, he went and tould his Lord, <hi>That I had neither eat nor drank in two days.</hi> Cardinal <hi>Chigie</hi> was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at it, and pittied my condition; and Cardinal <hi>Mancini</hi> telling <hi>him, that Monſieur</hi> Mazarine <hi>deſired I would Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire for fifteen Days into a</hi> Monaſtery, <hi>wherein there was a Siſter of Cardinal</hi> Mazarins; I took him at his VVord. My Brother and Siſter ſeeing the Deplorable State in which I was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to reflect upon their paſſed uſage to me, and could not be quiet until I had pardoned them.</p>
            <p>But I would not conſent that my Brother ſhould ſee me, yet at laſt they overcome me in this too; and though I ſaid that their Repentance could not redreſs the Injuries they had done my
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:45280:46"/>Reputation, the eaſineſs of my Nature carried me to yield even this time, notwithſtanding the juſt cauſe of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation which <hi>I</hi> had againſt them. <hi>I</hi> confeſs my Heart hardens at the Relation. <hi>I</hi> know nothing ſo Cruel in ones Life, as to ſee thoſe People come boldly to us that have done us unpardonable Injuries. It is enough to be mortally affronted by them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being perſecuted with their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance too.</p>
            <p>This Reflection with many others, which <hi>I</hi> had occaſion to make in my receſs made me reſolve to return into <hi>France,</hi> and to throw my ſelf at Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Mazarines</hi> Feet, and rather truſt to his Mercy without Capitulating, than to remain ſtill expoſed to as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more irkſome, and heart breaking adventures, as <hi>I</hi> had already run through. <hi>I</hi> made my Aunt <hi>Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nozzi</hi> to write to the Princeſſe of <hi>Conty</hi> her Daughter about it, and I was preparing to be gon as ſoon as the Anſwer was come, ſome few Days after <hi>Courbevil</hi> found means to let me underſtand, <hi>That after he had been ſome Dayes kept cloſe at Cardinal</hi>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:45280:47"/>Mancinies, <hi>he was conveyed to</hi> Civita Vetchia, <hi>where he had been a Priſoner for ſix Weeks: and where he was like to remain (as he ſent me word, long e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough) unleſs I would pleaſe to have the goodneſs to ſolicite for him.</hi> Though I had reaſon never more to concern my ſelf with him; yet becauſe I would not leave my Work imperfect, I begged his Liberty of <hi>Franciſco <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenzo Roſpiglioſi,</hi> the Popes Nephew, who thereupon commanded his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largment.</p>
            <p>In the intrim, the time which I was to ſtay in the Convent being elapſed, Cardinal <hi>Mancini</hi> made anſwer to the inſtances; my Siſter, unknown to me, had uſed to get me out of the Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, <hi>That he adviſed me to ſtay there a little longer, becauſe it would be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious for me, that the Anſwer which was expected out of</hi> France <hi>ſhould find me there;</hi> And this Anſwer was, <hi>That after I had remained two years in that Monaſtery,</hi> Monſ. <hi>Mazarine</hi> would conſider what he ſhould do with me.</p>
            <p>Cardinal <hi>Mancini</hi> by all means would have me ſubmit to this Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:45280:47"/>and truly in the great affliction of mind into which Monſ. <hi>Mazarine</hi>'s Harſhneſs had caſt me, I might have been perſwaded to any thing: But my Siſter would not let me ſtay there by no means; ſhe cauſed the Queen of <hi>Sweden</hi> to be ſolicited to that end, who gave me her promiſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive me into her houſe; all the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty was, how I ſhould make my E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape.</p>
            <p>My Siſter came to ſee me that After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon I intended it; and as we were packing up to be gone, and that <hi>Nanon</hi> was grown as broad as ſhe was long, with the Fardles, that ſhe had put round about her, every where under her cloaths; we had Intelligence that the Queen of <hi>Sweden,</hi> by the Advice of her Counſel, had retracted the Promiſe ſhe had given me. How un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome ſoever this News was, it was reſolved I ſhould make my Eſcape.</p>
            <p>My Siſter begun to take her leave to be gone, and I making as if I would wait upon her down Stairs; my Aunt <hi>Mazarine</hi> uſed all the Arguments ſhe
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:45280:48"/>had to oblige me to ſtay in my Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, becauſe I had been Ill along time; but I was not to commit ſuch an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</p>
            <p>My Siſters Children, not having the Liberty of coming within the Cloyſter, as ſhe had, and were brought that day on purpoſe to amuſe my Aunt in the Parlour; that we might not be peſtred with her, ſtayed for her at the Door, which as ſoon as the Abbeſs came to open, <hi>Nanon</hi> threw her ſelf out of it, as it were with Joy, to make much of them, and I after her. As they had no ſuſpicion of our Deſigne, the Lady Abbeſs durſt not ſtay me by force; nor had ſhe much time to conſider of it, for I was immediately got in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my Siſters Coach, and ſo drive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</p>
            <p>My Siſter had the priviledge, of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a certain number of Women with her into the Cloyſter, as often as ſhe came thither; my Aunt through vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and anger ſtopped two of them, that came in with her that day, though they were no way privy to our Plot: my poor old Aunt took the matter
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:45280:48"/>ſo much to heart, that ſhe dyed within few Dayes after, of the Diſpleaſure ſhe had taken for my Eſcape.</p>
            <p>We cauſed the Coach to drive ſtreight to Cardinal <hi>Chigies,</hi> to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore his protection, but we found him not; he came a little after to my Siſters, and ſeemed very cold in the matter, fearing the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; but his Holineſs made this Anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to Cardinal <hi>Mancinies</hi> complaint, <hi>That if he had known that I was kept againſt my Will in the Convent, he would have come himſelf to fetch me out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not being able yet to reſolve to live in my Siſters houſe, I went to lodge in the ſtreet called <hi>du Cours</hi> in our paternal Houſe, where the <hi>Roman Accadamy</hi> was ever kept. Cardinal <hi>Mancini</hi> was ſo angry at it, that he turned one of the Siſters out of the Houſe, who would have incommoded me if ſhe had ſtaid: But he ſoon after took the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of my abſence, being gone to <hi>Marrine,</hi> (to my Brother-in-laws) to ſeize, and take poſſeſſion of the Houſe: So that, I was forced at my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to take another.</p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:45280:49"/>
            <p>I was at length reduced to pawn my Jewels for my Subſiſtance: <hi>I</hi> had bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed but three thouſand Crowns up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, when I was informed the man that lent it me was in danger of breaking. But when I went to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem them, I found that Madam <hi>Martinozzi</hi> had prevented me, and paid the money, but would not return the Jewels. Whereupon the Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of <hi>Colonna</hi> taking no notice of her having them, prevailed ſo by his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Threats to this man, that he was forced to get them back from her; ſince he was not to let any Body have them, but thoſe that put them into his hands.</p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> was writ to, to redeem them; but he made anſwer, <hi>That there they ſhould ſtay for him, that I might be deprived of all wayes to ſubſiſt, the better to reduce me to my Duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> was neceſſitated to let one <hi>Grillon,</hi> a great Friend to my Brother, and the Conſtable, lay down the mony they lay in for, which I repayed in ſome ſmall time after.</p>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:45280:49"/>
            <p>The trouble of ſeeing my ſelf redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the Exigency of receiving Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations from people that might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe me in my need, and the ſtrait I was in, made me a little after reſolve to take a journey into <hi>France,</hi> to try to get a Penſion of Monſieur <hi>Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I went with my Brother, who was going to be married to Madamoiſel <hi>De Tiange:</hi> And it is to this Alliance that I owe the good Succeſs of my Voyage. We were neer ſix months upon the Road; when we were come to the <hi>Frontiers,</hi> we concluded that he ſhould go before, and that I ſhould ſtay behind, until he had taken the care that was neceſſary for my Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in <hi>France.</hi> But our Friends having given us an account of the Diſaſter of the poor Statues that were in the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace <hi>Mazarine,</hi> and that the Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture ſeemed favourable, we went together as far as <hi>Nevers,</hi> where he left me, and went on towards the Court in company with <hi>Grillon</hi> who o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertook us at <hi>Millain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As ſoon as Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood that we were upon the Road
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:45280:50"/>coming into <hi>France,</hi> he ſent <hi>Polaſtron,</hi> Captain of his Guards to inform him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf exactly of the Courſe of Life we lead, who raiſed all the Sheriffs and Provoſts about <hi>Nevers,</hi> to be aiding and aſſiſting to the Commiſſary, who came to put the Order of Parliament in Execution; whereby they were Authorized to Seize and Arreſt me. My Brother having complained to the the King of this proceeding, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty was in the mind to have ſent for me by his Authority; but Monſieur <hi>Colbert</hi> judging it more for my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to manage Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> as much as was poſſible. The King ſent him Command to ſigne an Order of Appointment that I might come quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to my Agreement; which he did with Tears in his Eyes; perceiving that if he did not do it, the King would proceed further in my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half.</p>
            <p>This Order came luckily to <hi>Nevers</hi> the ſame day that Monſieur <hi>Palluan,</hi> Counſeller of the <hi>Great Chamber,</hi> came thither to Arreſt me. I received like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe at the ſame time Command to come to the <hi>Lys:</hi> my Brother was
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:45280:50"/>married the ſame day that I arrived. Whilſt I was there, Monſieur <hi>Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine</hi> ſent to make ſeveral Overtures of Agreement with me; but it was by the mediation of a wretched ſort of People, in whom I could place no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, or without giving me any Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, that he would ſtand to any thing that ſhould be agreed upon. He told the King, <hi>That my Brother kept me off from coming to any Accord, and that he governed me with a Tyrannical Authority; and that if I did not ſtand ſo much in Awe of him, I ſhould be much more Tractable.</hi> The King to clear this Doubt, ſent for me three months after, by Madam <hi>Bellinzani,</hi> with an Officer, and ſome of his Guards, in Madam <hi>Colbert</hi>'s Coach; for, my Brother had begged of the King that I ſhould lodge at Madam <hi>Colbert</hi>'s Houſe, as a place where none ſhould be permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to force me to diſſemble my Thoughts. Two or three dayes after, he commanded I ſhould wait upon him at Madam <hi>De Mont Eſpan</hi>'s Houſe.</p>
            <p>I ſhall never forget his Goodneſs towards me; He prayed me to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:45280:51"/>
               <hi>That if he had not done better for me hitherto, it was my own Conduct that hindered him, and took from him the means; That I ſhould truly tell him what I would have done; That if I was abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely reſolved to return again into</hi> Italy, <hi>he would cauſe a Penſion of two thouſand four hundred Livers to be ſetled upon me: But that he adviſed me to ſtay; That he would make my Agreement as advantagious for me as I could deſire; That I ſhould not be obliged to follow Monſieur</hi> Mazarine <hi>in any of his Jur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys; That he ſhould have nothing to do with my Domeſticks; And that if his Careſſes were odious to me, I ſhould not be compelled to ſuffer them preſently; That he gave me until the next day to conſider of it, and give him my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I could eaſily have given him then the ſame Anſwer <hi>I</hi> made to him the next day; which was, <hi>That I could not conſent to return to Monſieur</hi> Mazarine, <hi>after having endeavoured to ruine my Reputation, as he had done; and after refuſing to receive me, when I ſent him offers from</hi> Rome <hi>to throw my ſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Arms, without any Capitulation or
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:45280:51"/>bartering for Conditions, at a time when he knew me reduced to the laſt Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of Want, and neceſſity: That in deſpight of all the Precautions that ſhould be taken againſt the Capriciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Humor, I ſhould be put to ſuffer a hundered little Injuries, with which, it would be very unfit to impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune His Majeſty upon all Occaſions. That I accepted of the Penſion with an humble and hearty Acknowledgment of His Majeſties great Favour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After ſuch juſt and lawful Reaſons, you will be ſurprized to hear that the World condemned my Reſolution Extreamely; but the Deſcants of Courtiers are very different from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men's Judgments. Amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Madam <hi>De Monteſpan,</hi> and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>Colbert,</hi> uſed all their beſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to perſwade me to ſtay; and Monſieur <hi>De Lauzun</hi> asked me, <hi>What I intended to do with my two thouſand four hundered Livers? That I ſhould ſquander them away at the firſt Inn I came to, and that I ſhould be compelled to come afterward with Shame and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion to ask for more, which would not
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:45280:52"/>be granted me.</hi> But he did not know, that my Wants had taught me how to husband my Mony. Not but that I perceived it was a thing almoſt impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, long to ſubſiſt handſomly upon this inconſiderable Allowance.</p>
            <p>But beſides that, <hi>I</hi> could get no more; and that Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> would not let me live at <hi>Paris</hi> without his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with me; <hi>I</hi> thought <hi>I</hi> might, with this help, gain time to take other mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> wanting other matter to beſpatter my Carriage, told the King, <hi>That I was making me a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſack to go dreſſed in man's Apparel.</hi> But his Majeſty was pleaſed to tell him, <hi>That he durſt paſs his Word, that I intended no ſuch thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Madam <hi>Belinzany</hi> had order with an Exempt of his Guards to conduct me to Rome, and to have two of His Guards to attend us to the <hi>Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I received ſo many Civilities from the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> in my paſſage through <hi>Turin,</hi> that <hi>I</hi> even then took a Reſolution, if ever <hi>I</hi> came to leave <hi>Rome,</hi> to come and take up my Receſs
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:45280:52"/>in his Territories. <hi>I</hi> arrived at <hi>Rome</hi> three months after, and ſome time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards <hi>Grillon</hi> came thither to plunge me, in ſpight of all <hi>I</hi> could do, into new Troubles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> had made a Reſolution to receive no Viſits from any, during my abode in <hi>France: Grillon</hi> pretending he ought to be excepted, becauſe of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice he had done me at <hi>Rome,</hi> in the Redeeming my Jewels; preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my Arrival there, he came once to the <hi>Lys,</hi> in the Counteſſes company, to viſit me. But <hi>I</hi> never would ſee him after. His Reſentment for this Refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal tranſported him beyond Belief.</p>
            <p>While <hi>I</hi> ſtayed for the Commiſſary at <hi>Nevers,</hi> my Brother's Steward, for my better Security, got me Lodgings in one of the Towers, of a Convent that was joyning to the Caſtle; and having but few Servants left me, he preferred to me one of my Brother's Guards, who had been turned out for ſome ſlight Fault.</p>
            <p>This man was very diligent in his place, to induce me to beg his pardon, in hope of which, <hi>I</hi> let him follow me to the <hi>Lys.</hi> A Raskal of a Cook
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:45280:53"/>of mine, to pleaſe <hi>Grillon,</hi> who had bribed him, goes and tells him, <hi>That this Wretch was very Officious, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to render himſelf neceſſary about me; and that he had ſometimes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe into the Convent. Grillon,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further Examination, reports this Story all about, to that height, that when <hi>I</hi> came to <hi>Paris,</hi> Madam <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> would not let this man ſtay in my Service within her Doors.</p>
            <p>Judge you in what amazement <hi>I</hi> was in, when <hi>I</hi> underſtood this Story, and with what Promptneſs <hi>I</hi> diſcharged my new Officer; and what my Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and juſt Indignation againſt this wicked <hi>Grillons</hi> villainy was; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>I</hi> was not ſurprized, as <hi>I</hi> paſſed through <hi>Lyons</hi> to ſee him have the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence to offer to come again into my ſight, under the pretence of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me a Letter from my Brother, to beg <hi>I</hi> would forget all. The indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and neglect <hi>I</hi> ſhewed him then, enraged him more than ever.</p>
            <p>When he came to <hi>Rome,</hi> he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood that Monſieur <hi>de Marſan</hi> came ſometimes to ſee me; and after a thouſand ridiculous Extravagancies
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:45280:53"/>that paſſed betwixt them, they had at laſt that idle Quarrel which you have heard of, wherein without much hurt to one another, they had the pleaſure once more to make me the ſubject of peoples talk. Sometime after this, my Siſter determined to retire into <hi>France,</hi> pretending ſeveral Cauſes of Complaint againſt the Conſtable; it would be too tedious to relate the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments I uſed to diſſwade her from this Journey, the diſpleaſures the like reſolution had drawn me into, made me more eloquent, but to no purpoſe; for the ſame Stars, or their influences, that drove me into <hi>Italy,</hi> drew her into <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As ſhe was always ſure of me, ſhe made no difficulty to draw me in to be of the party; and becauſe I had no tie at <hi>Rome</hi> when ſhe was not there, and that I believed I ſhould leſſen the dangers ſhe was to run through, by partaking and ſharing them with her, I did not ſtick to follow her. I only repreſented to her, <hi>how I ſhould be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to leave her as ſoon we were Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in</hi> France. Nothing was ſo griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to her, as this inavoidable neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:45280:54"/>and nothing perſwaded me more to yeeld to the force of her Reaſons, than to ſee that they brought her to conſent to our ſeparation.</p>
            <p>The Chevalier of <hi>Lorrain</hi> owed her greater Obligations than to fail to ſerve her in this occaſion, for ſhe quarrell'd with all <hi>Rome,</hi> upon his and his brothers account; they were welcom in no houſe in <hi>Rome</hi> but at hers; and ſhe had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared her ſelf for them in very nice points againſt Cardinal <hi>Chigi</hi> and the Conſtable himſelf. Yet for all this ſhe receaved no other Service from them, but huge and mighty promiſes of what they would do for her by their Credit in <hi>France;</hi> nor did they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form in that neither: as for her deſign the Chevalier thought it ſufficient to tell her; <hi>That if ſhe had no bodies Advice to guide her but her own, he ſhould be much concerned for her, but that ſince</hi> Madam <hi>Mazarine was of her Counſel, ſhe might reſt upon her Conduct, ſince ſhe had more Witt and more Courage than was needful for a much more hazardous Enterprize.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He litle thought then that he ſhould be called back into <hi>France</hi> ſo ſoon as he
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:45280:54"/>was; if he had done what he ought, we ſhould have been there long before him; and people would not have had occaſion to ſay, that we followed him: but my Siſter who relied wholly upon him, was forced to put off her Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney when ſhe ſaw her ſelf left in the Lurch by him. After his departure for <hi>France,</hi> ſhe brok her mind to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſon of Eminent Quality, whom ſhe believed her friend, becauſe ſhe had by her kindneſs and Favors Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him to be ſo. But he only told her, <hi>That the Chevalier of</hi> Lorraine <hi>ought to have helped her upon this occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> He asked me what I intended to do with my ſelf, and whether I had perſwaded my Siſter to this Voyage? He can yet juſtifie, that I made him this Anſwer. <hi>That I did not; that I knew I could not ſtay in</hi> France, <hi>neither was my intention at all to come there but under the Protection of a paſſport which the King of</hi> France <hi>ſent my Siſter for her ſelf and her Retinue; and that my deſigne was to retire into</hi> Savoy, <hi>as ſoon as I left her in a place of ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> In fine, having taken all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caution that humane prudence could think of, againſt any hazard that might
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:45280:55"/>beſal us in <hi>France,</hi> we order'd a Barque to attend us at <hi>Civita - vetchia.</hi> And upon a very fine Day in <hi>May,</hi> the Conſtable having told us at dinner, that he was to go twelve miles from <hi>Rome,</hi> to ſee his Stud, and that if he did not come home before it was late, we ſhould not look for him that Night. My Siſter would needs lay hold upon this occaſion, though we had nothing in readineſs to be gone. We left word that we were going to <hi>Freſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti;</hi> and ſo took only one of her Maids, and <hi>Nanon</hi> dreſſed in man's Apparel, as we were under our own Cloaths in my Coach: We came to <hi>Civitta - Vetchia</hi> about two of the Clock in the morning, when all the Gates were ſhut; ſo that, we were forced to drive into the middle of a thick Wood, there to wait until our Bark were found.</p>
            <p>My Groom of the Chambers, who took upon him to guide us, having run up and down a great while without find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, was fain to hire another, which he found there, for a Thouſand Crowns.</p>
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:45280:55"/>
            <p>While he was thus imployed, my Poſtilion impatient of having no Tid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings one way or other, took one of the Coach Horſes, and had the Luck to meet with our own Bark. But it was late when he came back: We were fain to walk five mile afoot to come to it; and ſo got on board a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout three of the Clock, without ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving eaten or drunk ſince we left <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our chiefeſt happineſs was, that we fell into the hands of a very honeſt and underſtanding Maſter; any other but him, would have thrown us over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board, after taking what we had, from us; for, he perceived as ſoon as he ſaw us, that we were no Beggars; and told us as much. His Crue asked us, <hi>If we had not kill'd the Pope?</hi> To ſhew you how skillful he was, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged his Way ſo well, that we came in eight dayes to <hi>Ciouta</hi> in Province, where we landed at Eleven a Clock at Night; From thence we arrived at <hi>Marſeiles</hi> about five in the morning, a Horſe-back; where we found the King's Orders, and the Paſt-ports, at the Preſident's Houſe.</p>
            <pb n="108" facs="tcp:45280:56"/>
            <p>The Conſtable moſt luckily ſtayd three Days away from <hi>Rome,</hi> and therefore it was late before he ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Truth. There was not a Fable ſo horrible to be invented by the wickedneſs of man, but was reported of us; to that Degree that they gave it out, that we were fled into <hi>Turkey,</hi> inſomuch that the Conſtable was fain to beg of the <hi>Pope</hi> to Excommunicate all thoſe that ſhould intermedle with, or talk of us. He diſpatched four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Courriers ſo many ſeveral ways after us; and one of them made ſuch haſt, that he got to <hi>Marſeiles</hi> before us. There came likewiſe thither a litle after one belonging to him, of thoſe kind of men, whom they call <hi>Brauos</hi> in <hi>Italy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Groom of the Chambers being gone, I knew not whither, to get Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries for his Journey to <hi>Paris,</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my Siſter was to ſend him. And we four Women were by our ſelves without other Company, in that very Inn to which this man came to lodge. <hi>Nanon</hi> ſaw him firſt, and knew him preſently; ſhe quickly gave us the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm; we ſent immediately to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendent,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:45280:56"/>to pray him to ſend us ſome Guards, which he inſtantly did. My Groom of the Chamber coming back from the Town, was deſired by this man to let him ſpeak to us, which he did, very civilly exhorting us to return back to <hi>Rome:</hi> But was glad to be gone thither himſelf, with the only Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of having a Letter from my Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to his Maſter.</p>
            <p>This Adventure made us go to lodge at the Intendant's houſe, and from thence, ſome few dayes after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, to <hi>Aix,</hi> where we ſtayed a month, and whither Madam <hi>de Grig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nan</hi> was ſo Charitable, as to ſend us ſome Shifts, adding, <hi>That we travelled like True</hi> Roman Heroines, <hi>with abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Jewels, but no clean Linnen.</hi> From thence, we went to <hi>Mirabeau;</hi> thence to <hi>Montpellier;</hi> Whence my Siſter went to Viſit Monſieur <hi>de Var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des;</hi> and from <hi>Montpellier</hi> to <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frein,</hi> where I learnt that <hi>Polaſtron</hi> was hard by coming from <hi>Paris</hi> under pretence of being ſent by Monſieur <hi>Mazarine</hi> to Complement my Siſter;
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:45280:57"/>But in truth, to cauſe me to be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted by Vertue of his damnable Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <p>When I heard of his coming, I walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alone, away into the Garden, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Fiſh-ponds, to let him paſs by; but when he found I was not with my Siſter, he would not ſtay, but pretends haſt to go on, thinking I was gone back, and ſo to overtake me; but he was miſtaken; for inſtead of following me, he went further from me.</p>
            <p>Thence I parted for <hi>Arles,</hi> by Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon the <hi>Rhone;</hi> from thence I went by Land to <hi>Martigues;</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by Sea to <hi>Nice,</hi> and from <hi>Nice</hi> to <hi>Turim,</hi> and ſo on to <hi>Mommeil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Siſter having taken the neceſſary Orders for my Security, from Monſieur <hi>L'Eſdignieres,</hi> ſent for me from <hi>Mom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meillan</hi> to <hi>Grenoble:</hi> To which place my Brother came to us, and ſtaid there with us ſeven or eight Dayes: and ſome eight Dayes after we dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted our Journey to <hi>Lyons:</hi> And my Siſter taking the Road to <hi>Paris,</hi> I
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:45280:57"/>took that of <hi>Chambery;</hi> where at laſt I found that Quiet, which I ſo long in vain had ſought for: and where I have remained ever ſince, with much more Calmneſſe and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity of mind, than a Woman as wretched, and as unhappy as my ſelf ſhould hope to enjoy.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:45280:58"/>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:45280:58"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEing deſirous to make this Hiſtory compleat, I have indeavoured to inform my ſelf of the Reaſons that induced the Dutcheſs of <hi>Mazarine</hi> to come for <hi>England</hi> (the French Edition having given no further account of her Affairs, then till her coming to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide at <hi>Chambery):</hi> The Motives, as I am informed, are theſe: That during the Life of the late Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> (in whoſe Territories ſhe then lived with ſo much ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, ſafety, and reſpect) She had no thoughts of removing from thence; but he being dead, ſhe did not judge her ſelf ſo ſecure; but that ſhe ought in prudence to find out ſome other place wherein ſhe might be at Covert from all the machina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of her Enemies: She therefore wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:45280:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>cast her eyes towards <hi>England,</hi> and conſidering the ſcituation of that Country ſo near <hi>France,</hi> that from thence ſhe might very Commodiouſly ſollicit her buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in all peace and ſecurity; reflecting likewiſe upon the generoſity of our King, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> by all thoſe that do him juſtice, to be a moſt obliging and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate Prince to all that put themſelves under his Protection: And moreover, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſufficiently informed of the temper of the Engliſh Nation, whoſe nature it is, not only to be civil and humain to all Strangers in general, but alſo to Love, Venerate, and pay all imaginable honours to perſons of worth and quality.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon theſe conſiderations, ſhe reſolved upon her Voyage hither, where ſhe ſafely arrived in <hi>December</hi> laſt, and has been received by the Court of <hi>England</hi> with all the demonſtrations of Honour and Civility due to her Vertues and Quality.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:45280:59"/>
            <head>THE LETTER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Returne you again the <hi>Memoires</hi> you were pleaſed to ſend me, by a Meſſenger expreſſe; fearing, leſt if I ſhould ſend them by the Poſt, they might run the ſame hazard, and fall into the like Inconveniencies, which at firſt brought them to your hands. If things ſo curious and well worth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercepting, were to be found every time the Miniſters of State ſhould think fit to open the <hi>Pacquets,</hi> I ſhould not much pitty the Commiſſaries trouble in executing their Orders. You had reaſon to believe, that after the manner I had ſpoken to you of Madam <hi>Mazarine,</hi> I ſhould be extreamly glad to ſee her Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory. It ſpeaks her own Genious, and is like her ſelf all over. I have particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:45280:60"/>obſerved twenty things in this Relation, that none but her ſelf could think, or expreſs in the manner they are penn'd.</p>
            <p>Since you ſay you never ſaw her, I will ſatisfie your Curioſity by endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to give you a rough Draught of her Face, and Shape of Body.</p>
            <p>She is one of thoſe lofty <hi>Roman</hi> Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, no way like our Baby Viſaged, and Puppet-like Faces of <hi>France;</hi> in whoſe Compoſition Nature alone triumphs over all thoſe Artificies and Helps, which our painted Ladies make uſe of, to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend themſelves, and their borrowed Graces to the doting World, and to the ſilly Adulations of their Conceited Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers.</p>
            <p>The Colour of her Eyes has no name; it is neither Blew, nor Gray, nor alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether Black; but a mixture of all three, which participates of all the Excellence that is found in them; they have the ſweetneſs of Blew, the Briskneſs of the Gray, and above all, the Fire of the Black; and what is more wonderful, you never ſaw more Lovely, and general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more Pleaſant, and more apt to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame, and yet nothing more ſerious,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:45280:60"/>more ſevere and ſteddy, when her Thoughts are taken up with any Grave Subject. They are ſo lively, and ſo quick, that when ſhe looks ſtedfaſtly vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any one, which ſhe rarely does, they think ſhe pierces their very Souls, and ſees into the very bottom of their Hearts. They are large, well ſlit, and decently rowling; full of ſprightly Life and Fire; and yet, with all theſe Beauties, they have nothing of Languiſhing nor Paſſionate; as if Nature maliciouſly had contrived them, onely to give Love and Veneration, and be ſuſceptible of none.</p>
            <p>Her Mouth is neither wide, nor very little; but the motion of her Lips are very Graceful, and Charming; and the ſtrangeſt Mouthes and Grimaſſes won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully becomes her, when ſhe imitates thoſe that make them. Her Smiles would ſoften the hardeſt Hearts, and eaſe the heaviest Sadneſs of mind: They do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt quite change the Ayre of her Face, which Naturally is Sublime and Grave, and ſpreads over it a certain Tincture of Sweetneſs, and Mildne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, that re-aſſures thoſe Hearts, which her Charms had A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmed, and inſpires them with that kind
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:45280:61"/>of unquiet Gladneſs, which is next of kin to a tender Inclination.</p>
            <p>So much for her Mouth and Eyes, which are the two chief Parts of her Face, moſt expreſſive, and principally im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant, to kindle a Flame and create Love; But the rest are nothing leſs to be admired and adored.</p>
            <p>Her <hi>Noſe,</hi> which without doubt, is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably well turned, and of a juſt Bigneſs, gives the reſt of her Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, a Curious, Noble, and Lofty Ayre, which is infinitly taking. The Tone of her <hi>Voice</hi> is ſo Harmonious and agreeable, that none can hear her ſpeak, without being ſenſibly moved. The Hue or Colour of her <hi>Skin,</hi> is Naturally moſt lively, and ſo delicately cleer, that I cannot believe, any man that views it with Curioſity, can juſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it to be whiter than the Driven Snow. The Colour of her <hi>Hair</hi> is ſhine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Black, but has nothing of Harſh; to ſee how Naturally they Curle, and into what fine Buckles they twine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as ſoon as they are let looſe, would make us think without much help of Poetry, that they ſwell'd with Pride; and, as it were, took a Glory in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:45280:61"/>they have to ſhade ſo lovely a Head: She has the fineſt turned <hi>Face,</hi> that ever <hi>Limner</hi> fancied, or drew with Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill.</p>
            <p>The proportion of her Body, though ſtraight and well framed, is nothing comparable to what it has been in deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of ſhape, before her cares made her neglect it, and wear looſe Garments. And for all that, many would fancy themſelves ſlender enough that were no groſſer than ſhe ſtill is. This makes her appear lower than ſhe is, though in Truth ſhe is of as becomming a height, as any Woman can well be without being Ridiculous.</p>
            <p>You ſhall ſee her for fifteen days toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in as many ſeveral Head - dreſſes, without being able to diſtinguiſh which of them ſuits her Face the beſt; and thoſe Droſſes, which would make other Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men look like <hi>Witches,</hi> wonderfully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come her; ſo hat no kind of Coiffing, or Head - geere, is unbecoming when ſhe wears it: the ſame thing is remarkable in her Cloaths, and Attire, you muſt ſee her lapped in a Night-Goun to Judge with more exactneſs of her. And it is in this perſon alone that one truly may ſay,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:45280:62"/>that Art, though never ſo cunningly u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and skilfully layed, can never equal Nature.</p>
            <p>Though ſhe loves Perfumes, Eſſences, and Aromatick Seents, ſhe never carries any about her, which ſhews undeniably, that that ſweetneſs is natural to her, which coſts other Ladies ſo much paines and Charges.</p>
            <p>I had almoſt forgot to ſpeak of her Neck, her Arms and Hands; but let it ſuffice, that they appear to have been made and fitted for the Face. And if we may Judg by what we ſee, of what we do not ſee, we may certainly conclude that her Husband after having been the happieſt man, is now the unhappieſt in the World. Thus ſhee is made as to her Body; and of the Mind, you may Judg, by what I am going to ſay.</p>
            <p>Being ſome time ſince at <hi>Rome,</hi> it was my chance to be ſpeaking of her af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner I heard her talked of at <hi>Paris,</hi> that ſhe was a fine young Lady, extream handſome, but guiddy, inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate, and extravagantly Head-ſtrong, and good-natur'd even to Folly. An <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> that knew her, hearing me give her ſuch a Charracter, Laughed in my
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:45280:62"/>Face after ſuch a manner that I was much ſurpriſed at it; but would never let me know why, though I had very earneſtly urged him to tell me his Reaſon. As theſe people dive further into mens Natures to find their true and proper Character than we do in <hi>France,</hi> ſo this adventure gave me a great Curioſity to ſee her as I paſſed in my return from <hi>Rome</hi> by <hi>Chambery;</hi> though I had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver much ſpoken to her in <hi>Paris,</hi> yet ſhe knew me by ſight, and by name.</p>
            <p>I was at first ſurprized, not to perceive in her at my coming, that eagerneſs and exceſſive Deſire to hear News, which is ordinary to thoſe that live at a diſtance from Court, when they ſee any that comes from thence. She received me as uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, as the most indifferent Woman of the Country could do. And inſtead of breaking my Head with Questions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the People and Affairs, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned her ſelf, ſhe entertained me only up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of my Journey, and other like things, wherein none but my ſelf was concerned: I thought my ſelf bound in Civility, to put her upon the Diſcourſe of her Friends and Relations, in <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Paris,</hi> ſince ſhe of her ſelf would not
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:45280:63"/>ſtart the Queſtion. I found that Subject was not unpleaſing, by the Attention ſhe gave to what I ſaid upon it; ſhe ſpoke ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villy of all People, and with a great deal of Reſpect of her Husband; but this Diſcourſe held no longer than I continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it. She rarely asked any Queſtions, and thoſe only which civility ſeemed to oblige her to.</p>
            <p>Neither could I mark in her either Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity or Inquiſitiveneſs. Wondering at her cold Indifference, I had a mind to put her upon the Diſcourſe of the things I thought moſt ſenſible to her, but with the Reſpect that was convenient, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her <hi>Fame,</hi> and her <hi>Fortune:</hi> But I could never hear from her the leaſt Complaint. Me thought I read ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Sadneſs in her Countenance, when her Reputation was in Debate. But for all other Matters, ſhe ſeemed to think that blind Goddeſſe, <hi>Fortune,</hi> a fitter Object of her Contempt, than Anger. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Perſon of Quality, of both Sexes came in while I was there; and among others, two or three Gentlemen that were of good Wit and Parts.</p>
            <p>The Ladies began to talk of the News of the Town; though the Dutches took
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:45280:63"/>neither ſides part, ſhe diſcourſed with the ſame Heat as others did; the Subject of their Converſation was a Diſpute that was betwixt two eminent men, whoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt was equally Great, and who ſhared moſt part of that Country betwixt them: She entred upon the Particularities, which were told her of the Cauſes of their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, weighed every little Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance with ſuch nicety and inſight, as if ſhe had not had two Millions for her Portion.</p>
            <p>The Gentlemen, whom I before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, altered the Diſcourſe, and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her, whether ſhe would or no, to talk of State-Affairs, as moſt worthy of her Attention and Contemplation. After every Body had paſſed their Verdict, ſhe was obliged in Complaiſance to ſpeak hers: thoſe that differed in Opinion from her, Vigorouſly urged their Reaſons: the Diſpute grew hot. She never defended her Opinion, but with Reaſons, of which ſhe made thoſe, that had not declared themſelves againſt her, her Judges. And I aſſure you I never heard any ſpeak ſo well, and with ſo much Submiſſion. This is what I remarked in this my firſt Viſit; and what I have obſerved ſince is as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:45280:64"/>
            <p>It is not to be diſcerned of what Humour ſhe is; and to ſpeak properly, ſhe has none at all; for every individual Perſon that converſes with her, has cauſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve ſhe is of his. She is not Obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bent upon any thing; and it is aſtoniſhing to ſee her quit even thoſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſements, ſhe ſeems the moſt pleaſed with, as freely as if ſhe were weary of them; Whence it clearly appears, that ſhe is eagerly carryed to no one thing, and ſhews that this eaſineſs of her Temper, and Manners, does not proceed from Levity or Fickleneſs, but rather from a profound Indifference for all thoſe vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Fancies, which troubles and diſquiets the minds of moſt People.</p>
            <p>Her ſweetneſs and Humanity, which above all, adorne and grace her Sex, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear even in her moſt Robuſt Paſs-times: ſhe is as much Miſtreſs of her Temper upon the Road, or a Hunting. as in her Cloſet. The Calmneſs and Equality of her Soul, is proof againſt all thoſe Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions which do unſettle and tranſports all others. She laughs at all thoſe Fidle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faddle fooling Amuſements to which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers abandon themſelves. Some other Women have don the ſame things that ſhe
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:45280:64"/>ſhe does: But ſhe does them another way.</p>
            <p>All People converſe in her Houſe with a Familiarity, full of <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect;</hi> the which nevertheleſs would be to her very incommode, and troubleſome, if ſhe were leſs good, or leſs obliging. Though ſhe be naturally very reſerved, and loves to be retired, yet generally all the Hours of the Day, are publick hours with her. The moſt private Receſſes of her Houſe are as open to thoſe that come into it, as the moſt common, and therefore it often happens that people come even to her very Cloſet Dore when ſhe leaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects any. Her Domeſticks, that ſee none come that are not as much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to her as themſelves, have inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly uſed themſelves to let all come in, and go out, with this kind of frankneſs and Liberty.</p>
            <p>It is Credible ſhe would have it ſo ſince they permit it; for ſhe is the Life and the Soul of her Family, and her <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, her Civility, and her obliging wayes are infuſed, unto thoſe that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it, proportionably as each ones Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city is fitted to imitate them. There is no Convent where they lead a more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:45280:65"/>Life then in her Womens Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whither a Page dares not approach upon pain of my Ladies Diſpleaſures, which is ſomthing more Terrible than the Rod. And for the Men, they live toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with that Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion ſo much the more Commendable, as it is moſt rare, and ſeldome to be found in great Mens Houſes.</p>
            <p>She alone of all Women, can play with her Servants without leſſening her ſelf, Her Preſence doth baniſh their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption without taking away their free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and it is not to be Comprehended how ſhe can give them ſo much Awe, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them with ſo much Familiarity, unleſs it be becauſe ſhe has ſo much of Grandure in her Carriage and all her wayes. There are they, that think it ſtrange, that ſhe ſhould delight in theſe kind of pastimes; but who ever will take the paines to look a little nearer, he will ſoon find that they are not the delight of Heart, and that thoſe ſhe uſes, are but ſo many ſeveral wayes of diſpelling thoſe afflicting Thoughts which the preſent ſtate of Her Fortune Croud's upon her.</p>
            <p>There is no private Gentlemans houſe more orderly, and regular than hers;
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:45280:65"/>and as her penſions is very inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make her ſubſiſt with that honour ſhe does, ſhe muſt needs be admirably skill'd in oeconomy, and her Acts of libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, and Magnificence, ſhew that her good management proceed (from an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary ſtrength of Reaſon. She neither much admires nor deſpiſes any thing. She never ſhewed the leaſt diſguſt againſt the Country, nor any thing that is in it; ſhe loves the Recreations, Cuſtomes, and Ceremonies that are there in uſe, as much as if ſhe had been born and bred there; others would aſſiſt at them, with marks of Complaiſance, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, and Deſtraction, which would caſily diſtinguiſh them from the reſt of the Company; but ſhe comes to them with that Familiarity, with that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and freedom of mind ſo uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, ſo conſtant, and ſo agreeable, that a ſtranger that ſhould chance to ſee her there, without knowing who ſhe was, would eſteem <hi>Savoy</hi> moſt happy in the product of ſo charming a Creature. She avoids ſpeaking of her own Greatneſs and Riches, with the ſame care and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, as others ſeek out occaſions to make people ſenſible of theirs.</p>
            <pb n="128" facs="tcp:45280:66"/>
            <p>It depends not of her way of living, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them; but that the Women of that Country, that ſee her, may think themſelves as great Ladies as ſhe; and may think <hi>Chambery</hi> as Noble and as Pleaſant to live in as <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Paris:</hi> and her Converſation there, as edifying, and as agreeable, as ever ſhe enjoyed elſe-where.</p>
            <p>Never did great Lady take leſs care to make her Inferiours ſee the Difference that is betwixt her and them; and if they do not forget it, ſhe is the more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to their Diſcretion, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect: for ſhe takes little pains to put them in mind of it.</p>
            <p>She judges of her ſelf, according to the Idea, or Opinion, ſhe has conceived of her own Merit, even in the moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Applications of thoſe that ſpoke to her, and ſhe as often takes juſt and due Commendations, for groſs Flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, as other VVomen take Apparent and Hypocritical Adulations, for true and deſerved Praiſes.</p>
            <p>It is a great ſigne, that her Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſincere, becauſe ſhe is Obſtinate in nothing; and being urged, will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge truly whatſoever is good, or fair
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:45280:66"/>in her. She is in nothing more unjuſt, than in not allowing what ſhe has of Admirable and Excellent, to be more than paſſable and ordinary. Though by ſad Experience ſhe has found, that there is very little Truth, Honeſty, or Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the World; &amp; that ſhe has juſt cauſe to think ill of all mankind, yet ſuch is her Naturall goodneſs, that ſhe never applies this her bad Opinion to any one in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; ſhe firſt excepts from the General Rule, all thoſe in whom ſhe perceives any Appearance of Vertue; but is much ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized when ſhe has reaſon to believe, they did not deſerve that Exception.</p>
            <p>When ſhe is obliged to ſay ſomthing ſhe thinks may diſpleaſe, a litle to ſweeten and take away the ſharpneſs of the Senſe, ſhe ſpeaks it ſo, as if ſhe had let it fall by chance; but ſhe thinks her ſelf no way wronged, to believe that ſhe ſayes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but what ſhe would ſay; it is more natural to her to be ſecret, than to other Women not to be ſo. Moreover ſhe is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually skil'd both in well ſpeaking, and holding her Tongue. Though it be a great Truth, that thoſe that know how to ſpeak well, know not how to hold their
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:45280:67"/>Tongues; and thoſe that can be ſilent, can ſeldome ſpeak very well.</p>
            <p>A Gentleman of very good parts and underſtanding, that had ſeen her, and known her a great while, aſſured me that ſhe is very much altered from what ſhe has been formerly, in ſo much that you would hardly know her again; but it is not to be comprehended, that ſhe ſhould be ſo much changed, without al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing that ſhe muſt always have had a prodigious ſtock of the Choiſeſt, richeſt, and moſt laſting Natural Beauty that ever Woman had. If her misfortunes have contributed any thing to her Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, never bad Cauſe produced ſo good an Effect.</p>
            <closer>I am <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>&amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:45280:67"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <head type="sub">The <hi>Reader</hi> is deſired to Correct theſe following <hi>Errata's</hi> as they Occur.</head>
            <p>PAge 10. line 20. read <hi>Potiers</hi> for <hi>Pontois.</hi> p. 13. l. 4 r. <hi>alſo more diſpleaſed.</hi> p 14. l. 5. r. <hi>Months</hi> f. <hi>Month.</hi> p. 16 l. 5. r. <hi>Siſter</hi> f. <hi>Siſters.</hi> p. 18. l. 18. r. <hi>Generoſity</hi> f. <hi>Generaſity.</hi> p. 11. l. 11. r. <hi>her Son his,</hi> and dele <hi>my.</hi> p. 24. l. 7. r. <hi>to ſee her.</hi> p. 33. l. 12. r. <hi>ſeeming</hi> f. <hi>ſcorning.</hi> p. 34. l. 12. r. <hi>Nanberre</hi> f. <hi>Nantare.</hi> p. 36. laſt l. r. <hi>Mazarine</hi> f. <hi>Marine.</hi> p. 41. l. 4. r. <hi>he</hi> f. <hi>ſhe.</hi> p. 41. l. 13. r. <hi>at the Abbey.</hi> p. 44 l. 13 dele <hi>it.</hi> p. 49. l. 20. r. <hi>ſubſiſt</hi> ſ. <hi>ſubject.</hi> p. 59. l. 12. r. <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mids</hi> ſ. <hi>amidſt.</hi> p. 58. l. 7. r. <hi>ran</hi> f. <hi>run.</hi> p. 61. l. 1. r. <hi>parmillac</hi> ſ. <hi>parnullac.</hi> p. 70 l. 15. &amp; 21. p. <hi>Narciſſus.</hi> p. 71. l. 12. r. <hi>to have had.</hi> l 20 dele <hi>me</hi> l. 23 r. <hi>the</hi> f. <hi>his</hi> p. 72 l. 19 r. <hi>their face</hi> ſ. <hi>of face</hi> p. 73 l. 19 r. <hi>Maſter</hi> f. <hi>Maſters</hi> p 74 l 3 r <hi>ſometime</hi> ſ. <hi>ſometimes</hi> p 77 l 18 r <hi>Hortenſia</hi> p 79 l 5 r <hi>Navaille</hi> p 86 l 1 dele <hi>him.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
